<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An essay to the restoring of our decayed trade wherein is described the smugglers, lawyers, and officers frauds, &amp;c. / by Joseph Trevers.</title>
            <author>Trevers, Joseph.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63134</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2130</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23763</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07892807</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07892807</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40315</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63134)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40315)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1216:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An essay to the restoring of our decayed trade wherein is described the smugglers, lawyers, and officers frauds, &amp;c. / by Joseph Trevers.</title>
                  <author>Trevers, Joseph.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[9], 59, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Widdowes, John Sims and Will. Milward,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"In laudem authoris &amp; subjecti" signed R.S.: p. 57-59.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wool industry --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Commerce.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Commercial policy.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40315:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40315:1"/>
            <p>AN ESSAY To the Reſtoring of our Decayed TRADE.</p>
            <p>Wherein is Deſcribed, the SMUGLERS, LAVVYERS, AND OFFICERS Frauds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>JOSEPH TRE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ERS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON Printed for <hi>Giles Widdowes,</hi> at the <hi>Green Dragon</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls Church</hi>-Yard, <hi>John Sims</hi> at the <hi>King's Head</hi> at <hi>Sweetings Alley</hi> end in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> near the <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi> and <hi>Will. Milward</hi> Stationer a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall</hi> door in <hi>New-Pallace-Yard,</hi> 1677.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:40315:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40315:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. THat no Nation hath ſuch advantages where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to inrich themſelves, as <hi>England</hi> hath.</item>
               <item>2. That the private Exportation of our wooll and Fullers Earth, doth exceedingly binder the Trade of this Kingdome, as alſo doth the private Importation of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Prohibited Goods.</item>
               <item>3. The ignorance of our common People of the Law in ſuch caſes, and want of incouragement to the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verers.</item>
               <item>4. The great loſs our Silk and Ribbon-Weavers.</item>
               <item>5. That the Trade of Clothing is the cheifeſt thing in the Nation.</item>
               <item>6. The profit gained by working up our Wooll by our own poor people, is almoſt unſpeakable, and influential to all degrees of perſons in the Kingdome.</item>
               <item>7. That there is loſt Millions <hi>per annum</hi> to the King and Kingdome, in Cuſtomes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by loſing our Trade of Clothing.</item>
               <item>8. That no other Country affords Wooll to make good cloth without our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wooll and Fullers Earth.</item>
               <item>9. A recital of ſeveral Statutes concerning Wooll, and the Tranſportation thereof, ſetling the <hi>Aulangers</hi> Office, and for the well making of Cloth, and the abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of our good Lawes.</item>
               <item>10. Setting forth the induſtry of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and other Countries, whereby in a great meaſure they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine our Trade.</item>
               <item>11, How the decay of Trade occaſions the Poor to be ſo numerous, brings Rents low, and conſequently Poverty to the Kingdome.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:40315:3"/>12. Several Quaeries Propounded, by way of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy.</item>
            </list>
            <byline>By,
A true friend to his Countrey,
JO. TREVERS.</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:40315:3"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>EDWARD SEYMOUR,</hi> SPEAKER of the Right Honourable Houſe of COMMONS; Treaſurer of His Majeſties Royal Navy, and one of His Majeſties moſt Honourable Privy <hi>CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NCEL.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FOr me to ſpeake of the Nobility and Worth of your Anceſtors, and the Noble Family (moſt Honoured Sir) would be but as an Eclipſe of the Sun by the Moon, which is the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net that moves in the loweſt Orbe, but laying a ſide all ſuch thoughts, the Occaſion of the Dedication of this enſuing Treatiſe to your Honour, is,</p>
            <p n="1">Firſt, for that you are ſignally Elected to be the <hi>Speaker</hi> of the Honourable the Houſe of <hi>Commons,</hi> the Repreſentative of the Kingdome, wherein ſuch Lawes are framed and ſetled, as are conducible to the Weal, Honour, and Safety thereof.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb facs="tcp:40315:4"/>2. Becauſe your Honours Abilities are ſo pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely manifeſt, as that you are likewiſe ſingled out to be one of his Majeſties moſt Honourable Privy Councel.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And that which doth very much move me hereto is, becauſe your converſe hath been much in, and about the Counties of <hi>Devon. Summerſet,</hi> and <hi>Wilts.</hi> where the Trade of Clothing is very much uſed, and therefore it may in all reaſon be deemed, that your Honours knowledge of (and acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with) Clothiers and their Imployments is more than ordinary.</p>
            <p>Sir the great Ambition I have to manifeſt my Loyalty to the King, and my zeal to ſerve the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, puts me upon theſe endeavours, to diſcover not only the advantages by our Manufactures, and the diſadvantages to the Kingdome by the ceſſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof, but alſo the great Frauds and Abuſes in the Out-Ports by the Cuſtome-Officers, which when reduced and brought into a better Method, by thoſe cheif Officers that are concerned therein, I hope it may prove a good Balſome to heal our wounds, and a Cordial to our drooping ſpirits.</p>
            <p>It is well known that the improvement of our Manufactures in this Nation hath a communicative influence upon thouſands of young and old people; yea ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> that are now idle and looſe people, have been more numerouſly imploy'd formerly, than now they are, by reaſon of the decay of Trade, which if it ſhould thus continue, or grow worſe, might be a great means to depopulate the Nation, and to draw great burdens upon many Pariſhes for the
<pb facs="tcp:40315:4"/>
maintenance of their Poor, but if not timely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, will cauſe the Trade to be driven by For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigner, and ſo exceedingly cauſe an abatement of Rents among us.</p>
            <p>Sir, your publique Imployment, your generous and Courteous Deportment, give me confidence to Dedicate theſe Rude and Unpoliſht lines to your view, becauſe I know, you have Ability to judge, and Charity to pardon the <hi>Errata's</hi> that you may find therein.</p>
            <p>When I did firſt ſet Pen to Paper about this matter, I found my ſelf in a Labyrinth, and there might have ſuffered, had not my Education as a Clothier given me a glimmering light to extricate my ſelf. And yet when I had purchaſed my En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement, by my ſtrict enquiery into thoſe Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, I had a great diſpute with my ſelf, whether I ſhould put my Abortive thoughts into Print or no, but more reſpecting the common good, than my private Reputation, I reſolved rather to make my wiſhes publique, than to bury them in Oblivion.</p>
            <p>Now Sir, it is not only a pleaſant ſtudy for States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to promote the Publike good, but the only way to true and laſting Honour, and Happineſs; and that theſe poor Endeavours of mine may attain that good effect to the King and Countrey, as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally deſign; (aiming at no other, I earneſtly beg of God to direct you for the Improvement of them, in your publique imployments, which may (like the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Heaven) break open the Springs of Trade <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap>ary and thirſty Land, to revive and refreſh the
<pb facs="tcp:40315:5"/>
ſame, and by ſo doing, Sir, you will not only do eminent ſervice to the King, great kindneſs to your Countrey, but alſo oblige all people to pray for your happineſs both in this world, and that which is to come, for the which alſo moſt earneſtly prates,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours moſt humble, and moſt devoted Servant,
JOSEPH TREVERS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:40315:5"/>
            <head>To his Honoured Friend, Cap. <hi>Joſeph Travers,</hi> on his Book Entituled</head>
            <head type="sub">An Eſſay to the Reſtoring of our decayed Trade.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <lg>
                  <l>IF I a Poet were, I'de undertake,</l>
                  <l>To write ſome Verſes for the Authors ſake.</l>
                  <l>And give him commendation for his pains</l>
                  <l>For I beleive, no more will be his gains.</l>
                  <l>For ſuch men as do mind the publique good</l>
                  <l>Their merits are but ſlightly underſtood</l>
                  <l>Yet unto laſting age their fame ſhall bud.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Author of this Book who took the care</l>
                  <l>Exactly to obſerve the great affair</l>
                  <l>Of this our Kingdome, which conſiſts in Trade,</l>
                  <l>Of Clothes and Stuffes which of our Wooll are made,</l>
                  <l>Hath here the profit clearly ſhewn to us,</l>
                  <l>And what advantage yearly cometh thus</l>
                  <l>If we were wiſe to be induſtrious.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Together with the miſchieſs that do come</l>
                  <l>On the whole Kingdome by neglect of ſome,</l>
                  <l>And treachery of others which is worſe,</l>
                  <l>(A heavier and more Prodigious curſe</l>
                  <l>Cannot well lighten on the Engliſh Nation)</l>
                  <l>To ſend away our Wooll by Tranſportation,</l>
                  <l>This if not cur'd will bring to deſolation.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>As much as in them lies for ſelfiſh ends</l>
                  <l>Such bring deſtruction to their beſt friends,</l>
                  <l>Firſt to the Soveraign Majeſty of the King,</l>
                  <l>Then to the Common-wealth, for this doth bring</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:40315:6"/>The Nation to be exceeding poor</l>
                  <l>And many Clothiers forced to give ore</l>
                  <l>Their Trading, and follow it no more.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But now I hope for better things to come</l>
                  <l>By the removal and diſplaceing ſome</l>
                  <l>Of thoſe that were in truſt, and put in ſuch</l>
                  <l>As are upright, and won't comply with <hi>Dutch,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor any Forreign Nation to invade</l>
                  <l>The Ancient Priviledges of our Trade</l>
                  <l>The want hereof makes <hi>England</hi> greatly fade.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>R. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <lg>
                  <l>Goe little Book into the world and ſee</l>
                  <l>Who thou can'ſt find therein to welcome thee,</l>
                  <l>I'm ſure thou mean'ſt as well to every man</l>
                  <l>Of all degrees and ſorts as any can:</l>
                  <l>From King to meaneſt, thou doſt wiſh them well</l>
                  <l>And therefore this thy Book doth truly tell</l>
                  <l>Of wrongs and of Abuſes done to all.</l>
                  <l>Then let them in whoſe compaſs it may fall</l>
                  <l>Soon rectify the ſame, and bring on Trade</l>
                  <l>A freſh, this is the end this Book was made.</l>
               </lg>
               <byline>Incerti Authoris<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </byline>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb facs="tcp:40315:6"/>
            <head>AN ESSAY To the Reſtoring of our decayed TRADE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat I may proceed in as good an Order as I can, (although I cannot pretend to Learning, or Ability to Compoſe a Book in a Methodical way,) but do wiſh that ſuch a task as this, had been undertaken by ſome other, that might have been able abundantly better to have mannaged it, to ſatisfaction of the <hi>Reader;</hi> Yet by reaſon of my former imployment, in the Trade of a Cloathier, and afterwards in the Office of Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyor of one of the Ports of this Kingdom, at the <hi>Cuſtom-Houſe,</hi> I am experimentally enabled to ſpeak to thoſe things, which ſhall follow.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:40315:7"/>And if there fall not out ſuch an Harmonious Order, in the enſuing Diſcourſe, by the neceſſary connection, or orderly introduction of one thing to another, as might be expected, (as before in my Epiſtle ſo again,) I do humbly beg the beſt and moſt favorable conſtruction, and cenſure of the matter; for having in my breaſt, the true heart, and Spirit of an <hi>Engliſh-Man,</hi> for his King and Country; I cannot bear with thoſe dayly abuſes, and evil practices, ſo frequently and notoriouſly put upon the King and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, but that I do reckon my ſelf Obliged, in all duty and good conſcience to my King and Country, to make them as publiquely known and manifeſt as I can, and then leave the Remedies, to be provided and anſwerably applied, by the Miniſters of State, which I hope in a ſhort time will be effected.</p>
            <p>And here I ſhall endeavour, Firſt, to make it to appear, that there is no Nation nor Kingdom in the World, that hath thoſe advantages, whereby to inrich themſelves, as this our Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> by the Manufacture of our Wooll, and conſequently to maintain our ſtrength, and<note place="margin">The Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage by the Manufac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Wooll.</note> Honor; omitting to ſpeak of many other ſtaple Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, of this our Kingdom, though many Rich and Profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, becauſe I am intended to Treat principally about the Subject of Wooll, and the Manufactures thereof, with the dependancies thereupon.</p>
            <p>Now that ſuch advantages as might accrue to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom are not laid hold on, and the Commodities improoved to what it might be, is too too evident to all men, that have<note place="margin">Wooll not improoved</note> any feeling of the caſe, or that do make any inſpection into it; which may alſo be ſufficiently confirmed to all others, by the ſad complaints, and frequent moanes, that are dayly made concerning the miſerable decay of Trade, to the great loſs of many perticuler men, and to the King, and Nation in General, and principally in the Trade of Cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:40315:7"/>But if the Wooll of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooved to the beſt advantages, and ſecured from expor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to Forreigners, doubtleſs <hi>England</hi> would be the General Market for the whole Univerſe, for matter of Cloathing, and what would ſoon be the Riches, great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Splendor thereof, (<hi>by the Almighties bleſſing</hi>) is not a thing very difficult to be imagined, by any ſober judicious Perſon, Merchant, or Traveller.</p>
            <p>And that no Nation hath ſuch good Wooll, for the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral<note place="margin">No Wool ſo good as <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
               </note> Trade of Cloathing is evident, elce what makes ſo many Forreigners of other Nations, ſo greedy of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wooll, if they had as good, or near as good of their own, and how highly was it formerly eſteemed, by the <hi>Dukes</hi> of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> and what benefit and advantage did that People under his government make of it; when they paid but ſixpence the pound for our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wooll, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned it to us in Cloath at Ten ſhillings the Yard; by which may very eaſily be computed, what profit did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to that people, in the working up the Wooll, which thing occaſioned many <hi>Engliſh</hi> Families, to tranſport them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into thoſe parts, for their profitable livelihood and ſubſiſtence.</p>
            <p>But after the Victorious Conqueſt, made by <hi>Edward</hi> the<note place="margin">Cloathing ſet up in <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> third, of <hi>Famous Memory,</hi> he cauſed to be ordered and ſet up the Manufactures of Wooll in this Kingdom, to the great increaſe of the Riches of his own People; the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of whom, for his provident care for the wellfare of his People; is worthy to be perpetuated to all ſucceeding Generations.</p>
            <p>And what now a days makes <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> ſo covetous of our Wooll and what large quantities by ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſter<note place="margin">Forreigners do covet our Wooll.</note> meanes, do they procure to ſerve themſelves, and their Countries; and what Riches do they acquire to themſelves thereby, may in ſome meaſure be gueſſed at, for by having our good <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wooll, they can mix their own courſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40315:8"/>
Wooll with it, and ſo make good Cloath, or Stuffes, which otherwiſe they could not do.</p>
            <p>To inſtance perticulerly in the <hi>French,</hi> it is taken for granted, and ſufficiently known, that their Wooll is very courſe, and of it ſelf fit for little, but to make a ſort of Cloath which is worn by <hi>Sea-men,</hi> and <hi>Fiſher-men,</hi> &amp;c. But by the help of our good Wooll; they make very good work, and ſend to other parts of the World their drug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And by having our good <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wooll, they can ſpend two or three Packs of their own Wooll, mixing it with ours,<note place="margin">Much <hi>French</hi> Wooll wrought up by mixing with ours.</note> by which meanes they make their Cloath and Stuffes paſs very acceptably, both among themſelves, and other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: Yea we our ſelves in <hi>England</hi> not being ſo wiſe, as we ſhould be, for our own advantage, do buy the <hi>French</hi> druggets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Made of our Wooll, mixed with theirs, and give great Prices for them too; when we do, or at leaſt may make better of our own.</p>
            <p>The care then being taken for granted, that <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wooll is the beſt, and moſt fit for Cloathing, Stuffes, Stockins, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How neceſſary may it be rationally ſuppoſed then, for our own People to be imployd in the working up our own Wooll, and how many thouſands would be imploy'd of the Poorer ſort of people, about ſuch work, who might there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by,<note place="margin">Poor to be Imploy'd.</note> gain to themſelves a very comfortable living, and free the Kingdom from thoſe great burdens in maintenance of the Poor; they being able by their Labour, (<hi>if Imploy'd</hi>) comfortably to provide for themſelves; for it is not the numerous multitude of people in a Kingdom, or Common Wealth, that makes it to be Poor, that they cannot live one by another, but the contrary, if all were imploy'd, and ſet at work, as there is imployment enough to be had, they would prove the eſpecial meanes, to make a Kingdom Rich; as may be clearly inſtanced by the <hi>Dutch,</hi> how many ſcores of thouſands of their Poor people are imployed about the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40315:8"/>
Herring Fiſhing, which makes them very Rich, and brings in yearly, near two Millions of Money, or other commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities neceſſary for the Land, which are equivalent to Money, beſides what they ſpend in the Land; this may ſeem to ſome to be a thing incredible, but I am able to make it cleare to any intelligent Perſon.</p>
            <p>Thus then by the neglect of our own Manufactures of our Wooll, flowes in like an inundation, the poverty of the Land; and hence ariſe thoſe ſad complaints, that fill every<note place="margin">Poverty for want of Imploy.</note> mans Eares, throughout the Kingdom, Alas! What ſhall we do to live, we have no Imployment; for if the Trade of the world abroad, for Cloath and Stuffes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Be ſupplied from other Lands, which make their Cloath and Stuffes of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wooll, being <hi>Clandeſtinely</hi> Tranſported into Forreign parts; our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Trade for that commodity, muſt anſwerably decay; and if the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchant hath not vent for that commodity abroad, to other Nations, the Country Cloathier muſt ſtrike off in a great meaſure, and conſequently many of the Poor work folkes, are anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably taken off from their imployments, which formerly for many years, they had been exerciſed in, and ſo having no work, they get no Money, and ſo are reduced to a beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging condition, or worſe: theſe things are to be diſcerned clearly, without the help of a Perſpective-Glaſs, by thoſe that are in any meaſure intelligent in Politique affaires.</p>
            <p>Thus the profit of the Poor, that they ſhould get to themſelves for a maintenance is loſt, and the profit gotten by their labour to the Kingdom is alſo loſt, in the General,<note place="margin">Profit loſt.</note> and this is brought to paſs by the quickſightedneſs, and diligence of our Neighbour Nations; who finding dayly the ſweetneſs of the Trade, and ſo exceedingly enriching themſelves, by our commodity, <hi>Viz.</hi> Wooll; doe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour more and more, to carry it on to their own ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, whiles we in <hi>England,</hi> in the mean time neglect our own opportunities, and advantages, which do ſo clearely lie before us.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:40315:9"/>From what hath been before hinted, doth neceſſarily<note place="margin">Loſs to the Kingdom.</note> follow the vaſt dammage, and prejudice done to this our own Nation, and Kingdom, by the exportation of our Wooll; for the dammage doth evidently appear, thus.</p>
            <p>Had not the <hi>French</hi> our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wooll to work withall, they could not work up their own Wooll, into any Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures that ſhould be acceptable, or ſaleable in other Countries, no nor in their own Land, but they would be ready as formerly to buy our <hi>Engliſh</hi> commodities; but now having our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wooll ſo frequently among them, privately gotten from <hi>England,</hi> or <hi>Ireland;</hi> they mix their own Wooll with it, and work up two or three Packs of their courſe Wooll, with one pack of ours, ſo that every Pack of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wooll exported from us, and carried to <hi>France</hi> is treble loſs, if not more to <hi>England,</hi> and on the contrary ſo much profit to <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus then any man may perceive, how Rich other Countries grow by our means, by obtaining our commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity<note place="margin">Other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries grow Rich.</note> to work upon, and there People alſo do generally live at a lower rate, and work cheaper by the day or otherwiſe, than our People in <hi>England</hi> do, by which means they may afford to under-ſel us, as uſually they do at a Forreign<note place="margin">Underſel us.</note> Market, ſo that hereby they do acquire to themſelves, both good credit, as well as great profit: and this Originally as aforeſaid is by our commodity; which if it was carefully looked after, by the Officers of the Cuſtomes, in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports cheifly; there might be ſpeedily, a good ſtop put to this their Trade, for if they got not our wool from <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cuſtom Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithful.</note> or <hi>Ireland;</hi> they could not go on with this their Trade of Cloath and Stuffes, but the great negligence, or unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſs of ſome Officers, belonging to the Cuſtomes, is the Principal occaſion, of the exportation of our wooll into Forreign parts, and conſequently of the loſs of the Trade of the Nation, in ſo great a meaſure, in this perticuler; from whence followes clearely, and undeniably, the poverty of the Kingdom in general.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:40315:9"/>For one Trade depends upon another, as it is in the body natural, ſo it is in the body politique, in the body natural, one member depends upon another, and is ſerviceable to the other, by a natural Harmony and Correſpondence, even ſo doth one Trade, or occupation cloſely, and neceſſrily depend upon another, here in <hi>England,</hi> and ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nection there is in this point, that if one chiefe Trade fail, very many alſo do fall with it, more or leſs, according to their proximity, or remotenes from it, in their dependance, and this may be applied cheifly, and principally to the Trade<note place="margin">Cloathing Trade Failing.</note> of Cloathing, and the Manufacture of wooll in other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects; how many ſeveral Trades are there, that muſt of neceſſity depend on the Cloathing Trade, as <hi>Card-makers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Many other Trades fail alſo.</note> 
               <hi>Spinners, Weavers, Fullers, Dyers, Cloath-workers, Pack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> and thoſe Trades which make Tooles, and inſtruments for theſe; are not alſo the Farmers at work, in the mean time, to provide bread for all theſe People, and their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, and breeding up his <hi>Oxen, Sheep, Hogs,</hi> &amp;c. That they may have Meat to eate, are not the Merchants and Sea-men, imploy'd in a great meaſure by this Trade, and theſe laſt mentioned (<hi>the Sea-men</hi>) are the men, who prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally, and cheifly bring in the wealth of the Nation: the Gentry of the Land, and all ſorts of Shop-keepers, are the receivers of this profit, which the Sea-men by their adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and induſtry do bring into the Nation; all ſorts of <hi>Lawyers, Phiſitians,</hi> and <hi>Clergy-men,</hi> are receivers, and get their Money by their Tongues, while the <hi>Adventurous Merchant, and undaunted Marriner, carries on the Trade of the Nation,</hi> exporting our native ſtaple commodities<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (<hi>of the which through Gods abundant goodneſs,</hi>) this Land of ours is ſo well ſtored, in ſeveral perticulers, as might be inſtanced in <hi>Tin, Lead, Cloath, Stuffes, Stockins, Herrings,</hi> of which might be an hundred times as many if look't after, and Sale enough for them too, at Forreign Markets: but the <hi>Dutch</hi> run away with the profit of theſe goods, making two Barrels for our one; <hi>Pilchards</hi> are a very
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40315:10"/>
good commodity, of which we do get good ſtore in the <hi>Weſt Country,</hi> and they do bring in good profit to the Nation, either in Gold or Silver, or ſuch commodities, as the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſtands in need off.</p>
            <p>By what hath been ſaid, it plainly appears how from the higheſt to the loweſt, there is a neceſſary dependance of one imployment upon another, and the falling off from one general Trade, occaſions the ruin of many inferior Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who had ſubſiſtence for themſelves, and Families there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by; and this in our Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> is ſeated prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally, and cheifly, in the Trade of Cloathing, and the Manufacture of Wooll.</p>
            <p>So that upon the failing of this Trade, of which there is too great a ceſſation and decay, in many parts of this Kingdom, there comes in inevitably ſuch a general loſs, to the whole Nation, for firſt and moſt principally the King loſeth hereby, and that extreamly, not only becauſe his<note place="margin">The King Looſeth.</note> Subjects are not ſet at work, and ſo are unabled to live com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably, and to pay ſuch Taxes, and impoſitions, as are requiſite for his Majeſties ſupport, and defence againſt his powerful Enemies.</p>
            <p>Nor in that the Honor, and ſplendor of the Kingdom, is hereby ſo much advanced and promoted, as it might be, but alſo becauſe his Majeſty looſeth ſo great a revenue, which would accrue to him in his Cuſtomes, if the Cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Trade was carried on with Vigor, ſo that the effectual carrying on, or deſiſting from the Cloathing Trade, is of very high Concernment, and Importance to the King; in profit or loſs, and ſo it runs through the meaner ſort of People alſo, as hath allready in part been ſpoken to.</p>
            <p>For what Cuſtomes come in Yearly to his Majeſty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning<note place="margin">The Kings Cuſtom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note> the Manufactures of Wooll, in its ſeveral, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ſorts, of the Old and New Drapery, in all the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieties of Stuffes, made now a days, and Stockins, by being Tranſported to Forreign parts, and what ſtore of Money,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40315:10"/>
and other goods, (<hi>equivalent to Money</hi>) being neceſſary com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities for the Kingdom, do they bring in again, for our Cloath, Stuffs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo ſold or bartered; and what Cuſtoms again do all thoſe imported goods bring into His Majeſties Coffers, may not be difficult to be computed, beſides the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of ſo many Ships and Seamen, and training up young Seamen, than which nothing in this age of ours, is more neceſſary to be taken care about; for there is (<hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve</hi>) the greateſt want of this ſort of men in the Kingdom, for although there may be enough found in the Kingdom, to Man His Majeſties Royal <hi>Navy,</hi> and it may be ſome to ſpare, yet it is believed there are not neer enough for His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Service, and for Merchants ſervice too, which may many times be carried on both together, as occaſion may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire;</p>
            <p>And if we do but look back a little, to a few Generations paſt, we may ſoon find what high Advantages have accrued to His Majeſty in His Cuſtoms; and to the Kingdom in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, by the Cloathing trade, being lively managed by the<note place="margin">The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of Merchants.</note> Merchants, and what worthy and noble Companies of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, have been Aſſociated and Incorporated; whoſe Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding hath for the moſt part, conſiſted in Woollen cloaths, as in the Merchant Adventurers Trading to the <hi>Eaſt-lands,</hi> and in what eſteem their Agents and Factors were in Forreign parts, and how Rich and great their Stock and Treaſure hath been, in ſo much that they have been able to lend a very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable ſupply and aſſiſtance to the <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Queen</hi> upon any Occaſion; and Particularly and Eminently (<hi>may it be ſpoken to their Honor</hi>) their Aſſiſtance of <hi>Queen Elizabeth</hi> of moſt happy Memory, in the year Eighty Eight; and ſince upon any Occaſion of the like nature.</p>
            <p>Neither is here to be omitted that company which is called the <hi>Eaſt-land</hi> Company, whoſe principal Trading alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts<note place="margin">Eaſt land Company.</note> in the ſame commodity of Woollen-Cloaths, by which they do furniſh all thoſe Eaſtern Countries about the <hi>Baltick-Sea,</hi> and to <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> by which means alſo our diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40315:11"/>
of thoſe <hi>Northern</hi> parts of the World, have bin made very Evident, and well known to Us, to the great Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our <hi>Navigation</hi> to the <hi>Northward,</hi> as far as <hi>Green Land;</hi> and of late years hath given occaſion of that Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very about <hi>Hudſon</hi>'s Bay, commonly now called the <hi>North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt</hi> Paſſage, made by that ſtout and adventurous Seaman, Captain <hi>Zachariah Gillam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the main and chief Trades of all, are the <hi>Turkey</hi> and<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Turkey</hi> Company.</note> 
               <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Trades, and the Riches by thoſe Companies pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured, chiefly by Woollen-cloaths, So highly Advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the <hi>King</hi> in His Cuſtoms, to the Companies in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, and to the whole Kingdom in the general, as is not a thing eaſily to be known or computed.</p>
            <p>How the <hi>Turkey</hi> Company in particular by their diſcreet management of the Trade in thoſe parts, with that commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of Woollen-cloaths chiefly, do bring into <hi>England,</hi> all the rich Goods from all parts of the <hi>Streights,</hi> and how the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company, by their Trade in the ſame commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company.</note> (<hi>in a great meaſure</hi>) do purchaſe the Rich commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities of <hi>India, Perſia, China,</hi> and the <hi>South-ſeas,</hi> with the Odoriferous Drugs of <hi>Arabia,</hi> and all ſuch Goods as thoſe countries afford for neceſſary Uſe and Delight, although of late years the <hi>Dutch</hi> have wrought us out of a great part of the <hi>South-Sea</hi> Trade, of which more might be largely<note place="margin">The <hi>Dutch</hi> have ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our trade in the South ſeas.</note> ſpoken concerning their uſage of our <hi>Engliſh-men</hi> in thoſe parts; but that it hath bin already ſufficiently laid out in Print, to the view of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation.</p>
            <p>And to add a little to what was before intimated, what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent<note place="margin">Good ſhips built year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note> Ships are annually built and prepared for the ſervices of theſe two Honorable Companies, whoſe imployment as aforeſaid, is principally for the Exportation of our Woollen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloaths, and if we do look back but to thirty years paſt, four or five Ships of the <hi>Turk</hi>'s men of War durſt not adventure upon one of our <hi>Smirna</hi> Ships, and alſo how worthy is it of Conſideration, to take notice how many of our beſt Seamen,<note place="margin">Seamen bred up.</note> and Artiſts are bred up in thoſe imployments by the two laſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40315:11"/>
worthy Companies Imployment; So that beſides what Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue is brought to the <hi>King</hi> in his Cuſtoms, by theſe great Sea-Trades of theſe worthy Companies mentioned, both for the Exportation of their cloaths, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the Importa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all manner of Goods, by this Stock ſo purchaſed abroad in Forreign parts, our Merchants are grown marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous<note place="margin">Merchants grow rich.</note> Rich, in ſo much that they are able upon any neceſſary Occaſion that His Majeſty hath for Money, to furniſh him at<note place="margin">Can lend the King money.</note> a weeks warning; and that which is worthy the noting alſo, our Seamen are grown of late years to be the moſt famous in the world, to the great glory, honor, and ſafety of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and the Kingdom, and all this is evident by what hath bin ſaid, to ariſe chiefly (<hi>next to the bleſſing of Heaven</hi>) from the Manufacture of our Wool in <hi>England,</hi> by our own peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which how much it ought to be incouraged, and of what high concernment it is to the Honor, Wealth, and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of the Kingdom, let the Sober and Judicious conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</p>
            <p>And if I ſhould adventure to give my opinion freely, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the matter in hand, I am very much induced to believe, that were it not for the Cloathing-trade (<hi>which imploys ſo many Ships and Men into ſeveral other Countries, and for the value of our Cloaths bring their Goods, by which means the poor alſo are ſet on work</hi>) that a great part of the Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick and Commerce of the world would fail; and this Trade as formerly intimated, is, and may be moſt readily, roundly, and advantagiouſly driven in <hi>England;</hi> were we but ſo pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique and carefully, as to keep our Wooll to our ſelves and within the <hi>King</hi>'s Dominions of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and to ſet the people cloſly to their work again.</p>
            <p>And before I do leave the Argument I have ingaged in, let there be conſidered the good quantities of Cloath and Stuffs<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Engliſh</hi> Cloath and Stuffs ſerve all the world.</note> that did go over continually to <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Flanders,</hi> and by them there diſperſed otherways; the large quantities of Stuffs and Bays that are ſent over to <hi>Portugall,</hi> and thence Tranſported to <hi>Brazilia,</hi> &amp;c, with a very conſiderable num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40315:12"/>
of Cloaths and Stuffs that go to <hi>Spain,</hi> and by the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> Tranſported to the <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi> all over, the good quantities of <hi>Perpetuanies,</hi> and ſuch like Stuffs that are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried out for <hi>Guinea,</hi> together of late days, with the large ſtores of Broad-cloaths, Kerſies, Sarges Cottons, Penni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtons, Duffels (<hi>or Hogs</hi>) Tranſported to our own Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>New-England</hi> and <hi>Virginia,</hi> with what alſo muſt ſupply <hi>Barbadoes, Jamaica,</hi> and our other Iſlands in the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> and forreign Plantations; all which are the manufacture of Wooll.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Clothing more worth to England.</note> The Premiſes conſidered, I hope I may make bold to ſay, that ſetting aſide all the reſt of the Rich and Staple commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities of <hi>England,</hi> which nevertheleſs are as good as any Country can parrallel in the world, as Tinn, Lead, Iron, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> this very commodity produced from our Wooll, is of<note place="margin">than the commodity of any Coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>try what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.</note> more worth and value to <hi>England, (that is to ſay)</hi> will bring in more profit to the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> than all the Silks or rich commodities of any Country whatſoever; Yea doubtleſs more than all the Spices of the <hi>South-Seas,</hi> yea, I do believe, and I have reaſon enough to lead me ſo to do, than all the <hi>Spaniards</hi> Gold and Silver Mines in <hi>America;</hi> for none of theſe I am throughly perſwaded, can any way equallize that yearly Revenue, that doth, or may come into the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> by this one commodity diverſly made up of our Wooll.</p>
            <p>Neither doth any Nation in the world get ſo much by any of their Goods, as <hi>England</hi> doth by this, to the great en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riching and advancement of the Merchant, and the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies Stocks, trading and adventuring in theſe goods to Sea,<note place="margin">Encreaſe of Seamen</note> the enriching of His Majeſty, the encreaſe of our ſtrength in Shipping, and conſequently the breeding and training up of Seamen, and increaſe of them, wherein as before intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, a great part of the welfare &amp; ſafety of the Kingdom doth conſiſt in theſe our days: and the incouragement of whom is of great concernment to the Kingdom, as the caſe now ſtands with <hi>England</hi> and her neighboring Nations; or as the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40315:12"/>
caſe may hereafter fall out to be; for our Land is an Iſland, as is known well enough, not only to its Inhabitants, but to all <hi>Europe,</hi> and we have not, nor cannot have Caſtles and Garriſons round about the whole kingdom by the Sea-ſide to beat off a forreign Enemy, and to keep him from landing and invading our Nation; for in fair weather in Summer<note place="margin">The King's care. for the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of the Nation.</note> time, there may be landing in hundreds of places about the Kingdom, where there is neither Town nor Caſtle neer; but ſuch is His Majeſties great prudence and care for the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his Land and People, that he doth highly eſteem and promote the affairs of Shipping, more than ever any of his Royal Predeceſſors have done, well knowing that his Ships and Seamen are the ſtrength and ſecurity (<hi>next to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of the Almighty</hi>) of his whole kingdom.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now endeavor to give ſome particular account, but very briefly, of the Profits ariſing to <hi>England,</hi> by working up our Wooll into Cloth: every two pounds of Wooll which is worth about twenty pence, will make a yard of Karſey, worth five or ſix ſhillings; and every four pounds of Wooll, worth about three ſhillings four pence, will make a yard of broad-cloth, worth eleven or twelve ſhillings: ſo<note place="margin">Profit by working up wooll.</note> that two thirds, is the leaſt profit, that doth ariſe by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our Wool into Manufactures; which doth amount to above 230 pounds ſterling profit, in every Tun of Wooll ſo wrought up, accounting twenty hundred Engliſh wait to the Tun; ſo that if we ſhould ſuppoſe, but an hundred Tuns of Wooll tranſported, out of the Kingdome, in a year to <hi>France</hi> unwrought, it will amount to 22400ll. ſterling, which is ſo much clear loſs to the Kingdome, and trebble ſo much profit to <hi>France,</hi> by their working up three times ſo much of their own, with ours, as hath been formerly intimated: beſides, it is worthy of conſideration, that ſo many of our poor lye<note place="margin">Poor idle.</note> idle, and loſe their imployment, being ready to periſh for want of neceſſary food, notwithſtanding the great plenty in the Land; and no Kingdome hath the like advantages, for the imployment of the poor, in any Trade or occupation (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40315:13"/>
doors) whatſoever, as we have for the poor in his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties dominion of <hi>England,</hi> about the old and new Drape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: and yet thoſe poor, that had their hands full of work, in one kind or another, according to what they were moſt accuſtomed, either by ſorting of wooll, mixing, breaking, carding, ſpinning, ſpoling, quilling, weaving, making of cards, picking of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſels, and many other imployments, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the working up wooll into cloth, which have kept many thouſands of men women and children at work, who knew not how to get a penny another way; but by this way<note place="margin">Poor get Money if Imployed.</note> of working, could in ſome comfortable manner live. When the trade of clothing was driven roundly, one family, that doth not get twelve pence a week now, have then received twelve, fifteen or eighteen ſhillings a week, which money went round to the Farmer for proviſion, or to the Shopkeeper for neceſſaries for their Families, and this again to the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, or to the Landlords, according to each man's Trade, and correſpondence.</p>
            <p>So that the profit ariſing, by the working up of our Wooll into cloth or Stuffs here in <hi>England,</hi> by our own people is almoſt unſpeakable, and is the great and chief wheel in the Kingdome, to ſet all others at work, as hath been already in ſeveral Trades mentioned, and more do attend upon it, when it is made into cloth, as the Clothworkers, Drawers, Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Fullers, Packers, Merchants and Seamen.</p>
            <p>But then to enter into the conſideration of the contrary, what an unſpeakable loſs is it to the Kingdome, to have ſuch<note place="margin">Exporting Wooll.</note> a Trade fall to decay, and ſo many thouſands of poor muſt of neceſſity be multiplyed in the Land, which muſt beg, ſteal or ſtarve, for want of imployment. But what think you if three or four hundred Tuns of Wooll in a year be exported out of the Kingdome (for ſo I have been informed) what a ſtroke doth that give to the beating down of our Trade in <hi>England,</hi> and what a vaſt loſs comes thereby to the Kingdome; and<note place="margin">Fall of Rents.</note> may we not juſtly be induced to believe, that the decay of our Trade in this reſpect, doth occaſion the fall of the rents
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40315:13"/>
of Lands in the Countrey, and houſes in the City of <hi>London</hi> and elſe where; fo that the Nobility, and Gentry of the Kingdome, have a ſenſible feeling of the decay of this Trade of clothing, for all that the poor do get for their labour about<note place="margin">The poors labor profit to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> this Imployment, goes from them again to others, as hath been already intimated, and ſo the money goeth round ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to its figure, and paſſeth from one to another, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as one trade hath dependance upon another.</p>
            <p>It may not be here unſeaſonable, to inſert a word or two, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our Fullers Earth, for cloth cannot be perfectly fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed without our Fullers Earth, to ſcoure and cleanſe the fine<note place="margin">Fullers Earth car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried out of the Land.</note> clothes, that are milled with Caſtle ſope, and all other midling cloths that are fulled with Sope; ſo that none but courſe clothes that are milled with Medicine can be well done, without the aſſiſtance of our Fullers earth, except at a greater charge, neither is there any other Countrey, beſides our King's Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, that have any Fullers Earth like ours in <hi>England;</hi> &amp; it is ſo reported, that the <hi>Dutch</hi> have gotten enough of it into<note place="margin">Into <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Holland</hi> to ſerve them for many years to come, which was cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly tranſported out of the River of <hi>Medway, (alias Chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>) for we have none in <hi>England,</hi> but what is about <hi>Maid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone,</hi> on the ſaid River of <hi>Medway,</hi> that ever I could hear of, except at <hi>Wooburn</hi> in <hi>Bedfordſhire,</hi> which is an Inland<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>town, and many Miles from the Sea; yet I have been a dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent inquirer into this matter: ſo that if the Tranſportation of this commodity, into Forrein Countries, was carefully looked after, it could not poſſibly be carried out of the Land, without a diſcovery of it, eſpecially from the River of <hi>Med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way</hi> aforeſaid, ſo that forreigners muſt of neceſſity be at the greater charge, in finiſhing their clothes, which could not be done, without the help of our Fullers Earth. Now that there is a prohibition of Exportation of our Fullers Earth, to For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign parts, is well enough known to the Officers of the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome houſe, but it is not looked after as it ſhould be, for ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome of them are negligent, not regarding their duties, and behaving themſelves with that vigilance and circumſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40315:14"/>
as ſuch places of Truſt do neceſſarily call for at their hands; or elſe they wink at ſuch miſcarriages, and ſuffer our Fullers Earth to be carried away, as the like is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done concerning our Wooll.</p>
            <p>And although moſt part of our Lawes are binding enough with ſevere Penalties annexed to them, if they were but du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerved and well put into Execution, yet not one of ten thouſand doth know the Lawes of Prohibition throughout the Kingdom, and how to put them into Execution; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though<note place="margin">Wooll car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d to <hi>France.</hi> &amp;c.</note> many people do certainly know that Fullers Earth is certainly carried out of the River of <hi>Medway,</hi> (alias <hi>Chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>han,</hi>) and our Wooll commonly ſhipped off from <hi>Dover-Cliffs</hi> by night, from <hi>Rumney-Marſh,</hi> the Iſle of <hi>Wight, Purbeck,</hi> and about <hi>Waymouth,</hi> and in ſeveral other parts of <hi>England;</hi> and too much from <hi>Southhamton:</hi> under the pretence of an Allowance by the Law, for the ſupply of Jar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey; Yet no body doth, or dareth to proſecute the Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for the breach of our good and wholſome Laws, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the very principles of Nature in every man, teach him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Preſervation, and he that minds but that, is afraid to meddle with theſe offenders who are commonly Rich men, and ſtrengthened both with Money and Friends in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties where they dwell; ſo that every man that is willing to preſerve himſelf, his Eſtate and Family, is afraid of appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt theſe Tranſgreſſors in the behalf of the <hi>King,</hi> though it be never ſo much conducible to the good and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of the whole Kingdom; for fear they ſhould be dealt withal as I have been.</p>
            <p>And while I am ſpeaking about the negligence and unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of the Officers of the Cuſtoms; give me leave in two or three words for a Digreſſion concerning the importation of Forrein prohibited Commodities, to the utter ruine of many poor Tradeſmen, with their Families in this our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; as Ribbon Weavers, and Silk weavers, and other ſuch<note place="margin">Tradeſmen undone.</note> like Artificers in &amp; about <hi>London,</hi> and ſeveral other parts of the Kingdom, that they are ſo miſerably Impoveriſhed that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40315:14"/>
they are ready to periſh for want of neceſſary food, to keep life and ſoul together; (as our Engliſh Proverb is) notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the great plenty of all ſorts of Proviſion in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, (through the goodneſs and bounty of God to us.)</p>
            <p>But all theſe errours, and miſcarriages, might and may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be prevented by the care and vigilancy of the Cuſtome Officers, eſpecially in the out-Ports: But ſome Officers finding a perticular, and preſent profit, by being inveſted with a Golden Livery, do rather chooſe that, than to do their King and Countrey faithful ſervice, although it be alſo running the hazard of loſing their preſent Imployment, and future Preferment; for things of this Nature, are now grown to that height of perfidiouſneſs, and confidence, (I might ſay<note place="margin">Smugglers proſecute honeſt men.</note> Impudence) that two or three golden Decoys are ſufficient to intrap an inclining Surveyor, and if there ſhould chance to be a diſcovery, or a ſurpriſal, there ſhall be all preſent help at hand, if need require, for the carrying off the matter ſmoothly, and Witneſſes in any caſe ſhall not be wanting, to<note place="margin">That diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover them.</note> counterfeit Truth and Juſtice, when it is directly contrary; by which malicious, and unnatural courſes, thoſe that would be juſt and honeſt in their places and Offices, are diſheartned, through the leud and deceitful practices, of theſe Catterpil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars; who by ſuch indirect Courſes are diſobedient to the Lawes, and the Smugglers that imploy them, do multiply great troubles, upon ſuch as at any time diſcover theſe Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, yea and do violently proſecute them at the Law, to make them Examples and terrors to others, that ſo they might drive on their cheating trade without controul; and yet ſuch honeſt well-minded men do nothing but their duty, but for that they have this <hi>odium</hi> caſt upon them, they are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Informing Knaves, &amp;c. notwithſtanding the welfare of the whole Kingdome, doth in a great meaſure depend upon the diſcovery of ſuch abuſes.</p>
            <p>How much neceſſary may it then be ſuppoſed that there ſhould be very good incouragement given to ſuch honeſt pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique ſpirited men, as ſhould diligently enquire after ſuch ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40315:15"/>
practices: and as it was before touched, thoſe Smug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers are not only well acquainted with ſome Attorneys and<note place="margin">Smugglers are befrien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</note> Clerks, who will either uſe undue practices, or make de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es; but they make good intereſt with the Under-Sheriffs, in the Countyes where they drive their Trade; and then theſe Underſheriffs alſo have ſtrange tricks and delays in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns, in which ſome of them will take part with the Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, inſtead of executing the Law againſt them, ſo that ſuch Offenders are incouraged; and by this means it is, that our Wooll and Fullers Earth, and other prohibited Goods, are exported ſo frequently out of the Kingdom, and Forrein prohibited Goods, and Merchandize imported; ſo that our Manufacture is in a great meaſure gone to decay: other Countries are greatly enriched, who alſo live at a lower rate, and work cheaper than our People in <hi>England,</hi> whereby our Trade is much taken off in Forrein parts, and our poor live idle, with the other inconveniences conſequent thereto, as hath been already ſpoken to.</p>
            <p>By this means it is, (<hi>in good part</hi>) that ſo much of the<note place="margin">Treaſure is exhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted.</note> Treaſure of the Kingdom is exhauſted and drawn away to other Lands; the general complaint now, <hi>being what ſhall we do, there is no Money ſtirring;</hi> and Lands are reduced to a lower value than formerly they were.</p>
            <p>Now, though all theſe Miſcheifes do not flow in at one time and place, yet it is like a Pond that is ſoon filled with many Springs, when as one Spring would do it in length of time: that which may ſeem to be at firſt but a ſmall Evil, will in proceſs of time with conſtant Practice, deſtroy the happineſs of the whole Kingdom; as a little Leak if not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of and amended, will in time ſink the greateſt<note place="margin">Unfaithful Officers.</note> Ship or empty the greateſt Ciſtern: even ſo will Offenders &amp; unfaithful Officers, being the only perſons in truſt with thoſe affairs, fill the Kingdom with Forrein prohibited goods and commodities, and empty it of our Wooll and Fullers Earth, with other prohibited goods; which evil Practices are now ſo frequent, that if not timely prevented by our Miniſters of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40315:15"/>
State, our Kingdom will be ſoon filled with Poverty, and emptied of Wealth and Happineſs, by this loſs of our Trade and Manufacture, which now is in ſo great danger of ſinking, (<hi>and that without all hope</hi>) unleſs thoſe that guide the Helm, do ſteer the great Concernments thereof into ſome ſecure Harbor, and there amend what may by ſearching be found amiſs, by diſplacing ſuch Officers as have proved in the leaſt unjuſt either by conniving at the Offenders or abetting and aſſiſting them, to the great diſcouragement of thoſe that are faithful in their Imployments; and that care alſo be taken that all due encouragement and countenance be ſhewed to ſuch as are found to be juſt, faithful, and exact obſervers of the Lawes that are extant againſt ſuch Smugglers and abuſive perſons.</p>
            <p>And without doubt, there is much Wooll Shipped off from <hi>Ireland</hi> annually, unto forreign parts; which might be<note place="margin">Wooll out of <hi>Ireland</hi>
               </note> as well wrought up in the countrey among themſelves, there being no want of people, and ſuch as for the moſt part live a lazy kind of life, (as I have credibly been informed) or elce their Wooll (if they work it not up) might ſoon be tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported over into <hi>England</hi> in twenty four hours time, or thereabout with a fair wind, and be wrought up in <hi>England,</hi> which would turn to a treble account of profit, as hath been already demonſtrated; but this I ſhall refer to others, that are more knowing in the Iriſh trade; but I am very apt to beleive the reports that I have heard, concerning great quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities of Wooll carryed from thence, both to <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> but to lay aſide the informations of others, although very well worthy of belief in all points, I ſhall according to my promiſe, in my Epiſtle, ſpeak to thoſe things of which I have had ſome large experience.</p>
            <p>I was a Clothier my ſelf, and Apprentice to the Trade, many years, and afterwards ſet up for my ſelf, and followed my Trade many years, thriving very well thereby, till about nineteen years agoe, that I was burnt out of all, and put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the adventures of fortune; and taking notice of the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currances
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40315:16"/>
of affairs, I did find large teſtimonies of the decay of Trade, with the occaſions thereof, but while I did keep the Trade going, I have rode far and near, to get Spinſters, and other work folkes, and gave great Wages, as alſo did all other Clothiers, and yet could not procure half ſo many as we would have imploy'd: but ſuddenly after our diſorders, and diſregard to our Lawes as aforeſaid, the Market fell, and many Clothiers were forced to leave off their Trades, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe<note place="margin">Clothiers leave off.</note> they could not vend their commodity.</p>
            <p>All thoſe poor people formerly ſo imploy'd, were ready to ſtarve for want of bread, in and about thoſe places, where the Clothiers left off and failed; and every day it grew worſe and worſe, and thoſe confuſions among us increaſed more &amp; more, that very few men were of one mind, and hardly any at all, that minded the publique good: but now ſome thoughts are buſied of reſtoring things to their Luſtre, and trade to what it was before the decay.</p>
            <p>Some wiſe men have been of the opinion, that the abating the intereſt of money, would greatly increaſe and advance trade, and very probable it might be a good lift to it.</p>
            <p>Others again, being out of hopes of the recovery of the former trade, think men muſt imploy their wits, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, in the invention of ſome new ſorts of Manufacture; and ſome covetous wretches, have been very ready to declare their opinion, that the increaſe of the intereſt of money, and the abatement of Servants and Workmens wages; to which, adding great frugality, and good husbandry, would make the Kingdome to be happy, and flouriſhing again; and many there are, that make it their buſineſs and ſtudy, to outwit and deſtroy other men, and under pretence of honeſty, and many by clandeſtine means, ſwallow up the good and pious gifts, of our Anceſtors, belonging to the Church and to the Poor; for in this our Iron age, men have left off to do good, and loft their obedience to the Lawes of the Land, and have ceaſed from the exerciſe of thoſe two unſpeakable graces, Faith and Charity.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:40315:16"/>And therefore truly I fear we have little hopes of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or being reſtored to our Priſtine flouriſhing condition,<note place="margin">Kingdome flouriſhed under King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt.</note> till we do return to our old obedience, and exerciſe our ſelves in love and good works, fearing God and honouring the King, and not giving our minds to change, but let every one endeavour to amend one, and ſtrike off from the error of his own waies, and endeavour his utmoſt to diſcharge a good conſcience, firſt to God, and then to mind the pulique good, calling to mind the happy condition of Trade in the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt of bleſſed memory, when all men dreaded his Lawes, and lived in love one with another, which made the Kingdome flouriſh, in our trading with great ſucceſs, and increaſe of Riches; and indeed we enjoyed ſo much happineſs as made us proud, and forgetful of God's mercies, and ſo murdered the beſt King in the world, by which we ſtript our ſelves of all but Gods juſt judgements upon the Nation, and left our ſelves certain of nothing but of uncertainties.</p>
            <p>I find by our good Lawes, that great care was<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> taken about Wooll, and all other prohibited commodities; as firſt in the Reign of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. then wooll was wholly prohibited to be exported, which was the firſt begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the promotion of making Cloth in <hi>England,</hi> but it ſeems the Nation at firſt could not work up all the Wooll, that was of our own growth, till the Trade was diſperſed throughout the whole Kingdome, and people inſtructed in the Art. So that an Act of Parliament was made for the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſportation of Wooll into other Countries, to a Staple ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, at firſt at <hi>Callis,</hi> paying their due Cuſtome firſt in <hi>England;</hi> ſo that thoſe which had our Wooll in thoſe daies<note place="margin">Staples appointed.</note> paid well for it: another Statute was made to this purpoſe, that if any Forreigner would have any of our Wooll out of <hi>England,</hi> and found none at the Staple, he was to bring to the King's Mint, an Ounce of Gold, as a d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty for every ſack of Wooll; and many other good Laws I find forthe prevention of Abuſes concerning Wooll and Cloath; and for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40315:17"/>
of the Tranſportation of Wooll, but what did firſt pay the King's duty in <hi>England;</hi> and was to the intent that our People might afford their Cloaths ſo, as to underſel Strangers; And ſeveral Staples were appointed in <hi>England</hi> where Wooll was to be ſold and bought, and not elſewhere; and none to be carried or lodged neer to the Water-ſide, nor bought nor bargained, but by <hi>Cloatheirs</hi> and ſuch as wrought it up, or by Merchants and their Factors under ſeveral Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties:<note place="margin">Many good Lawes made.</note> Many other good Laws have been made ſince the time of King <hi>Edward,</hi> for the keeping our Wooll and Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers-earth in <hi>England,</hi> to imploy our own poor People, and advance the Manufacture of the old and new Drapery, ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily ſet on foot by the prudence and diligence of that King, &amp; then there was Obedience from all perſons rendred to the good Laws of the Land; which good Laws have been Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively ever ſince continued, by almoſt every Parliament, with ſuch Additions or Exemplifications as were found to be neceſſary, for the prohibition of the Exportation of Wooll and Fullers-earth; by which means we both got, and kept the whole Manufacture of our own Wooll, and a good part of other Countries among our ſelves in this Kingdom, till the time of our late unhappy Confuſions.</p>
            <p>And if the Book called the <hi>Golden Fleece,</hi> with ſome of Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh's</hi> Works, which do fully demonſtrate the great bleſſings of God on this Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove any other, for the imployment of the poor people were well inſpected, and anſwerably improved, it would be a means to make the Kingdom happy and flouriſhing.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>I ſhall here give a brief Recital of ſeveral Statutes more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Wooll and Cloath.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, that no Cloath made beyond Seas, ſhall be brought<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stat. 15. of Ed. 3. ca.</hi> 8.</note> into the King's Dominions, on pain to forfeit the ſame,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stat. 15. of Ed. 3. ca.</hi> 5.</note> and to be further puniſhed at the King's will.</p>
               <p>That all <hi>Cloath-workers,</hi> and Artificers in the trade of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40315:17"/>
Cloathing that came out of other Countries into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, had the King's Protection to dwell where they pleaſed, and convenient Franchizes and great privilidges were at firſt allowed them for their incouragement; maintained at a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique charge out of the King's Exchequer.</p>
               <p>I find there that Strangers as well as Natives, might have<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stat. 18. of Ed. 3. cap.</hi> 3.</note> bought Wooll as they could agree, and that great care was taken to avoid Deceits, to abate and leſſen the prices of wooll, and to avoid falſe Packing, falſe Winding, and falſe Ballan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to have one juſt Weight throughout <hi>England,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and tried by the reſpective Sheriffs of every County, according to the Standard of the Exchequer: and that no buyer of Wooll, (Stat. 13. of <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. cap. 2.) ſhould make any refuſe or waſt, but an equal hand ſhould be carried be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween buyer and ſeller; and this upon grievous Forfeitures,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stat. 8. Hen. 6. ca.</hi> 22.</note> as Stat. 12. <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. cap. 9. Alſo that all Wooll-felles and Leather bought in the Countries, ſhould be brought to the Staples which were appointed on purpoſe, where Wooll and ſuch commodities were to beſold, and ſhould remain there<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stat. 23. H. 8. cap.</hi> 17.</note> fifteen days at leaſt, for the ſupply of our own people who were to have the firſt choice, or as much as they would work up, and then the remainer which could not be wrought up in <hi>England,</hi> were to be ſent to publique places in the day time,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stat. 31. Ed. 3. ca.</hi> 8.</note> and from thence to the Ports appointed on purpoſe for the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to be Tranſported, after the Buyers had paid their due Cuſtoms and Subſidies, (<hi>Viz.</hi>) for every ſack of Wooll, which contained 94 Pounds, 2 pounds 10 ſhillings: and for every 300 of Wooll-felles two pounds ten ſhillings, and for every laſt of Leather, five pounds; and that no wooll vendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stat. 13. E 3. cap.</hi> 9.</note> ſhould be lodged, ſhewed or ſold, within three miles of the Staple, by any Merchant, Buyer, or Tranſporter, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others, but ſuch as had of their own growth, and no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: And the Chancellour, Treaſurer, with the advice of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Kings Councel, had power to defer the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſportation of Wooll, when, and as often as they ſaw it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:40315:18"/>It was then ordered, that no Merchant of the Staple, ſhould<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stat. 2. of H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n.</hi> 5.</note> Tranſport Wooll, Woollfells, Lead, or Tin, without the King's Licence, until they were brought to the Staple, on pain to for feit the ſame.</p>
               <p>It was then made Fellony to Tranſport Wooll, by the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute<note place="margin">27. <hi>Ed. Ed 3. ca</hi> 3.</note> of the Staples, as you may find it concerning the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſportation of Wooll, by <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchants, but this Stature<note place="margin">28. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.</note> for Fellony was repealed, the 38 of <hi>Edw. 3. Stat.</hi> 1. and 6. and the forfeiture for Lands and Goods, was ſtill continued,<note place="margin">8 <hi>Hen. 5. cap.</hi> 2.</note> and in <hi>March</hi> the 37. of <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. the Staple for theſale of Wooll was fixed at <hi>Callis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then the Staple aforeſaid was removed from <hi>Callis,</hi> and clearly put down, 43. <hi>Edw. 3. Cap.</hi> 1. and the Staples ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed and fixed in <hi>England,</hi> at the places following: <hi>Viz.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stat. 47. E. 3. cap.</hi> 1.</note> at <hi>Neweaſtle, Kingſton</hi> upon <hi>Hull,</hi> St. <hi>Buttolphs Boſton, Yarmouth, Quinborough, Weſtminſter, Cheſter, Wincheſter, Exeter,</hi> and <hi>Briſtol,</hi> and the Staples of <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> were to be kept where firſt they were ordained, and ſeveral other good clauſes were added concerning the Regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Staples, as may be ſeen at large, in the Statute of the Staple, 27. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>It was there appointed, that all Merchants, Strangers,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sta. 8 Hen. 5. cap.</hi> 2.</note> that bought wooll in <hi>England,</hi> to conveigh to the <hi>Weſt</hi> parts, or elſewhere, that did not bring them to ſome of the Staples to be ſold, were to bring to the Maſter of the Kings Mint, for every ſack of Wooll which contained ninety four pounds, an ounce of Gold Bulloin, or the value in ſilver Bulloin, on pain to forfeit ſuch Wooll, or the value thereof to the King ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stat. 8. He. 5. cap.</hi> 2.</note> I alſo find that great care was taken that no perſons in <hi>Norfolke</hi> ſhould buy wooll there, and in divers other Countries thereabout, for fear they ſhould Tranſport it, but only thoſe Merchants which carried it to the Staples, or thoſe which did convert it into Yarn, Hats, Girdles or Cloth:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stat. 1. Ed. 6. cap.</hi> 6.</note> And that ſuch woolls as were bought in <hi>Norfolke,</hi> and <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich,</hi> and thoſe Countries, were to be ſold and retailed in the open Market, if not carryed to the Staples: And that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40315:18"/>
thoſe in <hi>Hallifax,</hi> were to ſell what Wooll they bought to<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stat.</hi> 2.</note> thoſe poor people in the town, or parts adjacent; who to their knowledge did work up the ſame into Cloth, or Yarn: and if the Wooll driver did ſell his wooll out of <hi>Hallifax,</hi> or if any of the town bought to ſell again, unwrought, into yarn, or cloth, every ſuch Offender did forfeit their double value of the wooll, ſo ſold, or uttered, the one half to the King, and the other half to the Proſecutor, and the Juſtices<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stat. 3. Ed. 4. Cap.</hi> 5.</note> of the Peace, in their Seſſions, were to determine the ſame. Many ſorts of wares and Merchandiſes were prohibited to be brought into the Realm, ready wrought, which were wrought and made by Hand-crafts-men.</p>
               <p>That all forreign Bone lace, cuttings, Embroydery, French<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stat. 14. cap.</hi> 121. 13.</note> Bandſtrings, buttons, needle-work, &amp;c. were prohibited to be brought into this Realm.</p>
               <p>Noneſhall export any ſheep, or wooll, wooll felles, Mart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stat. 12. cap.</hi> 2 32.</note> Yarn, Fullers earth, Fulling clay, nor carry, load, nor convey the ſame to be tranſported, upon ſeveral penalties. as well upon the owners of the ſheep, as the perſons that ſhall convey the ſame. This Statute at large is worth the peruſing, and might do much good to the Kingdome, if it was duly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, by all the Kings Subjects; but the behaviours of our people in <hi>England,</hi> are not as they were in former times, for then a Law was no ſooner made, but all men took immediate notice of it, and did willingly yield their obedience thereto; but the people have been ſo accuſtomed to the breach of Law, and Rebellion, that in reaſon, it cannot ſuddenly be forgotten, and deſiſted from, by many people, for men now adayes are grown ſo Critically wiſe to do evil, that let the King, with the advice of the Lords and Commons, make uſe of their beſt diſcretion, and judgements, in framing Laws for the publique good, and wording them according to the moſt proper ſence, by them intended, yet ſome ordinary fellow, that hath ſtore of confidence, and a little money, (and that it may be gained by Cheating too,) one way or another will find a hole in them, to tranſgreſs thoſe Lawes, and if they are called in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40315:19"/>
queſtion, then they have tricks and evil devices, enough to torment thoſe that do faithfully diſcharge their Oathes, and Conſciences for the publique good, as I my ſelf can ſpeak ſufficiently, concerning this and ſuch like caſes, by my ſad experience.</p>
               <p>It was made Fellony for any Engliſh, Welſh or Iriſh, to<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stat. 23 E.</hi> 3.</note> tranſport Wooll, wooll felles, Leather, Lead, &amp;c. and a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond clauſe in the laſt Act was, that no Engliſh, Welſh, or Iriſh-man ſhall tranſport any of the ſaid commodities, in any ſtrangers name, or keep a ſervant beyond the Seas, to ſurvey the ſale thereof, or to receive money therefore; a third clauſe in the ſaid Act was, that there ſhould be no exchange of wares for Merchandiſe of the Staple, but Gold or Silver, or Engliſh, Welch or Iriſh Merchandiſe, neither ſhall any Merchant make any confederacy, in fraud or deceipt to this Ordinance, upon the paines aforeſaid. A fourth Clauſe in the ſaid Act was, that it ſhould be lawful for every man to carry his own Wooll, Wooll felles, Leather or Lead, to the Staple, war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranting the packing of this Wooll.</p>
               <p>Merchants were prohibited the exporting the money,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stat. 4. H. 4. ca.</hi> 15.</note> which they received in <hi>England,</hi> for their Merchandiſe, and goods imported, but they were to lay out their money again, upon ſome of the Merchandiſe of this Realm, except their reaſonable Expences.</p>
               <p>All Merchants ſtrangers, were enjoyned to lay out their Money, they received for their Merchandiſe imported into<note place="margin">Stat. 17 E. 4. cap.</note> this Realm again, in ſome Merchandiſe of this Realm, and to prove the laying of their money ſo out, and by whom it was ſo layd out, before the Officers of the Port, where it was ſo diſpoſed of, or laid out, upon the penalty of forfeiting all his goods found within the Realm, and to ſuffer a years Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment.</p>
               <p>All Merchants ſtrangers were bound to give ſecurity, to<note place="margin">Stat. 15. Hen. 4. ca.</note> the King's Cuſtomer and Controller, to imploy their money upon the commodities of this Realm, their reaſonable coſts excepted, and Italian Merchants were to ſell their Goods
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:40315:19"/>
where they did land them in groſs, and not by retail, and their<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stat. 1. Ric. 3. cap.</hi> 16. 9.</note> money ſo received, to be laid out again in the Realm, within the ſpace of eight moneths.</p>
               <p>Theſe and ſuch like Statutes and Lawes might do very much good, to encreaſe the Tradeing of the kingdome, if they were enquired into, and revived with ſuch addition as might be neceſſary, for now we ſend all our money out of the Kingdome, and vend but ſmall quantities of our Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, but onely our native commodities, which are prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited, which quite ruines our Trade.</p>
               <p>It ſhall be Fellony for any that ſhall tranſport any Sheep,<note place="margin">14. <hi>cap. 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Stat.</hi> 14.</note> Wooll, wooll fells, martlings, ſhorlings, yarn made of wooll, wooll flocks, fullers earth, fulling clay, Tobacco-pipe clay, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> this Act I do beleive if not repealed, will do much inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry now adaies, although it was intended for publique good, for I fear it will hinder many people from diſcovering the Offenders, and breakers of the Law, though they were ſure to have never ſo great a reward for it, for many men will be very cautelous, how they touch the life of a man, though they do deſerve death, more a thouſand times than the Theif that robs on the High-way, for a Theif doth but take away part of a particular mans Eſtate, but theſe wretches that tranſgreſs the Kings Laws in tranſporting Wooll, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners, deſtroy as much as in them lyes, the happineſs of a whole Kingdome, and are the procuring cauſes and Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to bring many thouſands to great miſeries and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing deaths.</p>
               <p>There were many good Laws made, for the ſetling the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingers Office, and preventing frauds and deceipts in work, in all ſorts of Drapery, both old and new, which are too redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to recite, though many of them be very neceſſary to be obſerved, for the credit and reputation of our Manufacture, but I ſhall only ſet forth, where they are to be found, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the ingenious, and judicial, to the peruſal of the Statutes themſelves, which are the Statutes concerning Wooll and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:40315:20"/>
clothing. 25. <hi>of Edw. 3. Cap. 4. 27. Ed. 3. Stat. 4. 50. Ed. 3. Stat. 7. and 8. 3, Ric. 2. cap. 2. Stat. 7. Ric. 29. 13. Ri. 2. Stat. 10. 13. Ric. 2. Stat. 11. 17. Ric. 2. Stat. 2. and 13. 13 Hen. 4. Stat. 24. 9 Hen. 4. Stat. 2. 11 Hen. 4. Stat. 6. 11 Hen. 6. Stat. 9. 4 Ed. 4. Stat. 1. 7 Edw. 4. Stat. 2. 17 Edw. 4. Stat. 3. 7 Edw. 4. Stat. 5. 1 Rich. 3. Stat. 3. and 4. 3 Hen. 7. Stat. 7. and 71. 3 Hen. 8. Stat. 7. and 8. 5 Hen. 2. Stat. 8. 1 Hen. 8. Stat. 11. 6 Hen. 8. Stat. 9. 25 Hen. 8. Stat. 18. 27 Hen. 8. Stat. 11. 6 Hen. 8. Stat. 9. 25 Hen. 8. Stat. 18. 27 Hen. 8. and Stat. 13. 33 He. 8. Stat. 3. 33 Hen. 8. Stat. 19. 4 Eliz. 6. Stat. and 2. and 5. 3 Phil. and Mary 11. 4 and 5 Stat. 3 Phil. and M. Stat. 4 and 5. 5 Phil. and Mary Stat. 5. and 8. 7 Eliz. Stat. 12. 33 Eliz. Stat. 9. 27 Eliz. Stat. 18. 39 Eliz. Stat. 11. 29 Eliz. Stat,</hi> 20.</p>
               <p>Cards for Wooll, were prohibited to be brought out of other Countries into <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Wales;</hi> none were to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſport ſheep beyond Sea, without the King's Licence, there was a limitation upon keeping Sheep, and an appointment how many ſheep each man ſhould keep, upon the penalty of 3 Shill. 4 pence, for every ſheep more than his number.</p>
               <p>And if it be as the Company of Silk-Weavers, and Ribbon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weavers ſay, (as doubtleſs it is,) there are an hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand people ſmall and great, that depends upon that trade in and about the City of <hi>London;</hi> then how many may be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed rationally to be in the whole Kingdome, that have their dependance on the trade of clothing, in the old and new Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, and other Trades, which have a dependence upon, or relation unto the Trade of Clothing, and which know not how to earn a penny any other way, ſince that trade is in a great meaſure loſt, and leſt off; but theſe poor people live idly, and go a begging for their bread, among which alſo are many children from 8 years of age to 15. which can very well get a living about the trade of clothing, for that they can ſort Wooll, mixit, Spole, Quil, Pick Teaſels, prick Card<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiers, &amp;c. and which in the time of good trading, could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:40315:20"/>
earn eighteen pence, twenty pence or two ſhillings a week, but now very few of them, have any imployment as aforeſaid; and if I ſhould ſuppoſe but a Million of ſuch poor people, throughout the Kingdome, which ſhould every one<note place="margin">Loſs by the Poor not ſet at w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>k.</note> get his eighteen pence a week, it would amount to, Three Millions nine hundred thouſand pounds in a year, which is ſo much clear loſs to the Kingdome; beſides I know that there are many hundred thouſands more of ſuch people, which live idly, and get nothing. Since we have left off ſo much of the Clothing trade in <hi>England,</hi> as hath been already intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the evil effects and conſequents thereof, I humbly deſire to leave and commit to the conſideration of thoſe that are more judicious in the Political affairs of the Common-wealth, to have ſuitable Remedies, as to their grave wiſdeme and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence might ſeem to be meet and neceſſary, I endeavouring only to be a layer open of the ſore, and refer to the skilful Chyrurgeon for a healing Plaiſter.</p>
               <p>And if our Parliament men, and Miniſters of State ſhould take into their ſerious conſideration, the great troubles, that are multiplyed upon thoſe that endeavour faithfully to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the execution of the King's Laws, againſt the Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s to be Proſecuted.</note> cheifly intending thereby, a future prevention of their fraudulent dealings and threatning practices,) and would give incouragement to ſuch publique ſpirited men, by ſome eſpecial care taken, for the preſervation of their Credits and Reputations, and their perſons from troubleſome Arreſts, and vexatious Suits and moleſtations, which the Delinquents do multiply againſt them, by falſe and feigned Actions, and thoſe coloured over with very ſpecious pretences, but the truth and reality of their intentions and deſigns is, to ruine and deſtroy the Reputations, Eſtates and Families of ſuch as ſhall diſcover them, or appear againſt them. This I ſay (<hi>viz.</hi> the countenancing and encouraging of all faithful Officers and others,) would ſtrike a kind of terrour to theſe tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors, (Smugglers and others,) that do deceive his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:40315:21"/>
of his due Cuſtomes, and be a great means to keep them in awe, and good order, and encourage all men to be ready to diſcover ſuch Offenders, as they night any way find them out by their opportunities, being abroad early and late; and to add to this, that there ſhould be very ſevere Proſecutions<note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>niſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt of Offenders.</note> againſt ſuch Offenders, and let them be abated nothing of the Juſtice of the Law, which is in ſuch caſes provided, and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed throughout the Nation: for now it is a ſufficient crime, (as the caſe of late hath ſtood) to be by ſuch branded with the ignomy of an Informer, or an Informing Knave, though he diſcover nothing, but what doth immediately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the King's Intereſt and publique good. And by theſe <hi>Smugglers</hi> and their Companions, he ſhall be reputed and ſaid to be, a troubleſome fellow, an evil nei hbour, a diſturber of the Peace among friends, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> becauſe he doth faithful ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, according to his Duty, Conſcience, and Office, in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring to prevent their Frauds, and abuſes, as frequently by them practiſed as they can. And if ſuch Officers in the Cuſtomes, Atturneys and Clerks, which do connive or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with ſuch Offenders, were removed from their Places, and Offices, and ſeverely puniſhed, the publique good would be much preſerved, Trading greatly advanced, and thereby Gentlemens Eſtates largely augmented, in their yearly value of Rents.</p>
               <p>I ſhall now give a brief deſcription of ſeveral Springs, that fill our Kingdome with Prohibited goods, and of ſeveral Leaks, that empty the Kingdome of other ſorts of our goods, which are prohibited to be Exported out of the Nation: As our Wooll, and Fullers Earth, formerly ſpoke to, which are by ſtealth carryed out of the Kingdome, to the great damage and prejudice of the Nation, and many Forreign Prohibited<note place="margin">Injury to the Silk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weavers.</note> goods, are brought in among us, to the great injury, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing of many Tradeſmen; as Silk and Ribbon Weavers, and other Artificers in and about <hi>London,</hi> and ſeveral parts of the Kingdome, which occaſions the great decay and loſs of our own Manufacture, with the loſs of the imployment of the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:40315:21"/>
Poor, to the ruine of many thouſands, of men women and children, that have had their dependance, cheifly, if not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, on thoſe Merchandiſes, which are dayly Imported from <hi>France, Flanders,</hi> and other Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, ſecretly into this our Kingdome.</p>
               <p>There are many of our Sea-Port Towns, and ſeveral Creeks, and holes along the South-ſhore of <hi>England,</hi> beſides <hi>Dover, Rumney Fairlee, Haſtings, Foleſton, Rye, Bredhempſton, &amp;c.</hi> where theſe things are practiſed; and indeed in the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time, when it is fair weather, goods may be Landed on the Shoar, and Shipped off from the Shoar, on Veſſels all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the Coaſt, almoſt from <hi>Dover</hi> to the Lands end, in <hi>Cornwal;</hi> and many times there are both brought aſhore, and<note place="margin">Wooll Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d off.</note> carried off ſuch Goods as are Prohibited both wayes, both for coming into the Land, and carrying out of the Land, and this done in a fair night, and the goods brought in, lye ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in Countreymens houſes, which can hide and ſecure them till there be a convenient opportunity to diſpoſe otherwiſe of them with ſafety, and theſe Countreymen help them to Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, to carry them to <hi>London</hi> or other Markets.</p>
               <p>Neither do I here mention any thing of the North-Coaſt, becauſe I have hitherto been altogether unacquainted with thoſe parts, although I have reaſon to beleive, that the ſame Smuggling Trade is alſo practiſed in thoſe quarters, for their Coaſt lying over againſt <hi>Holland,</hi> doubtleſs the people there are as ready to comply privately, in forbidden tradeing with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> as along the South-Coaſt, they are with he <hi>French,</hi> notwithſtanding there is ſufficient Proviſion made, in our Lawes againſt ſuch ſiniſter and evil Practices: But a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Kent</hi> and <hi>Suſſex,</hi> are moſt frequently imported Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited goods from <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Flanders,</hi> and they are goods of ſuch value, that a ſingle Horſeman may arry five, or ſix hundred pounds worth about him, and yet it ſhall hardly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> be known that he hath any thing with him.</p>
               <p>Now if theſe things were well conſidered, what quantities of goods are privately imported, and ſo as that they are ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:40315:22"/>
diſcovered, with what alſo comes into the River of<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chatham</hi> River.</note> 
                  <hi>Medway</hi> (alias <hi>Chatham</hi>) which lies about twenty ſeven miles from <hi>London,</hi> by Land; and the moſt convenient River in <hi>England,</hi> (I beleive) to Land goods privately: it would eaſily appear, what loſs it is to his Majeſty in perticular, in his Cuſtomes, which by theſe and ſuch like Practies are ſtol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, and in general to the Trade of the whole Kingdome.</p>
               <p>It is alſo well known, that thoſe which ſteal the Duties of the King's Cuſtomes, and do Import and Export Prohibited Goods and Commodities, are none of the meaneſt perſons in the places where they dwell, but ſuch who oftentimes have great intereſt with the Magiſtrates about thoſe places, and ſeeing they get their money ſo eaſily, by not paying the Kings due Cuſtome for their goods, as honeſt Merchants do, and being Purſe-proud, do not value what they ſpend, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratiate themſelves into the favour of ſuch Gentlemen, as<note place="margin">Smuggl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y friends.</note> have authority as aforeſaid; and then make it their buſineſs by the aſſiſtance of ſuch Magiſtrates, and their countenance, to deſtroy all ſuch as ſhall diſcover their fraudulent dealings, or elce by ſome ſmall Bribes to ſtop their mouths, that ſo theſe Cheats may avoid the penalty of the Law, and prevent others from the future from diſcovering their doings.</p>
               <p>The King's Cuſtome houſes, ought to be ſo many locks and Keys to the Kingdome, to let what is warrantable and lawful to come in, and to keep out what is forbidden its en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance, and to prevent the great abuſes that are ſo frequently complained of, both in the Exportation of our Prohibited goods, and the Importation of Forreign goods forbidden by Law; and if the Officers were but as vigilant and faithful as they ought to be, they might eaſily and readily prevent theſe enormities with their care and diligence, which are ſo dayly practiſed.</p>
               <p>But it is too well known, how remiſs and careleſs the<note place="margin">Blank Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificates a Cheat.</note> Officers are, and neglectful of their duties in many of the out-Ports eſpecially, that it is a thing very uſual with Smug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glers to get blank Certificates, with the Seal of the Cuſtome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:40315:22"/>
to take up their Bonds that are given for the true de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery<note place="margin">Exchang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Viſſel.</note> of their goods at ſome other Port in <hi>England;</hi> and moreover there is a great cheat in the ſhifting Maſters of ſuch Veſſels, as take in ſuch goods, they will oftentimes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change the Maſter, before he goes out of the Liberty of the Port, where the goods were Shipped; and yet if all theſe things fail, and their coaſt Bonds come to be forfeited and put into Suit, it is not to be expreſt, the delayes, ſhifts and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful tricks that are practiſed by ſome underſheriffs and their Deputies, in their returns, and in the Execution of the Law, which ought to be done both with ſpeed and juſtice, but both theſe are by ſuch perſons omitted, and theſe kind of doings do highly incourage theſe offenders, in their ſinful practices.</p>
               <p>I have alſo obſerved that the Farming the King's Cuſtomes<note place="margin">Farming the King's Cuſtomes.</note> hath been an occaſion of great prejudice to the trade of the Kingdome, and the publique good; for when the weal and good of the whole Nation, comes in competition with the<note place="margin">Injury to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</note> preſent profit of the Farmers, they are apt to reſolve the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion for their own advantage, permitting Prohibited goods to be Landed, ſo long as the due Cuſtomes, for them come into their Coffers, and the under-Officers, knowing what the Farmers their Maſters do, are very apt to learn the trade, to let paſs our goods out of the Land that are alſo prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: and thoſe Smuggling Merchants that deal in ſuch kind of wares, can eaſily find out the blind ſide of ſuch Officers, &amp; that will be bribed, to wink at ſuch their deceitful practiſes, ſuch an unfaithful Officer ſhall be highly comme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ded among theſe theeviſh Merchants for a brave fellow, one that knows his buſineſs, and for a very civil perſon, that will do a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant a kindneſs upon occaſion. Thus evil is called good, and good is ſtiled evil, as I ſaid before; thoſe Officers that<note place="margin">Springs to fill us with Forreign goods.</note> are faithful to King and Countrey, are called Knaves, Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome fellowes, evil Neighbours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> theſe the honeſt good men '&amp;c. Good Lord! what a paſs are we come to in this Nation? people account it no ſin to ſteal from the King,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:40315:23"/>
and now a daies thoſe that practice ſuch things have changed the terme, it is not (by them) called ſtealing Cuſtome, but ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving cuſtome; for my part I am of the opinion, that he that ſteals Cuſtome from the King to the value of twenty ſhillings, deſerves to be puniſhed as well as he that ſteals ſo much from any other man. For as I heard a Scholler once a reaſoning, either it is this or that, &amp;c. ſo I ſay here, either Cuſtome is the Kings due, or it is not, but no man dares be ſo impudent as in words to deny it, but they muſt needs acknowledge it a truth, that it is his due, and if ſo, why then do they not give to <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that are his, according to the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Saviour, and the Commandement of the King, and Parliament, it being eſtabliſhed by Law, and conſtituted for the publique good, and the general advancement of the Trade of the Nation, and ſuch Officers as will not comply with theſe ſort of people to cheat the King, are called Fooles, men that do not know their buſineſs, but if another had that Office, he would make ſomething of it, &amp;c. but ſuch men minding the faithful and conſcionable diſcharge of their duty to God, to the King and Kingdome; with the bleſſing of God live better, and do a thouſand times more good than others, and may be principal Inſtruments to make the Kingdome hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py and flouriſhing.</p>
               <p>I have had diſcourſe with ſome perſons who have had the thoughts of getting a Pattent, to put the Laws into Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that are againſt the Tranſportation of Wooll, and other<note place="margin">Pattent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Tranſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Wooll</note> prohibited commodities; but I can hardly think they would be careful and diligent in that imployment, except they ſhould reap a conſiderable profit for their labour, how ſhould they expect to ballance their expence. I refer to the cenſure of the judicious, except it be by conniving at, (or<note place="margin">do more harm than good.</note> compounding with) the Offenders; ſo that by ſuch a deſign as this, the tranſgreſſors may be encouraged to ſin more, and more; for if ſuch Patentees ſhould too much diſcourage that ſort of people, that carry off the Wooll, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to other Nations, (who are the only men that muſt bring grifts to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:40315:23"/>
their Mill) it would be as ridiculous a thing, as for Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers to perſwade people to peace, and by that means loſe their Practice; and it is generally beleived, that there would be more Prohibited goods tranſported then, than what have been before, if the care for the putting the Lawes into Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, were once committed to Pattentees, for as in other caſes of the ſame nature, the love of Money is ſo natural, and money ſo much hunted after, that it may be acquired, that the minding of putting the Lawes into Execution, and men doing faithfully and uprightly their duty, is not a thing now a dayes at all regarded, or taken into conſideration as it ought to be.</p>
               <p>But I hope that his Majeſty with all the Peers of the Realm, and all others, are made in ſome good meaſure ſenſible of the great concernement of Trade, and the ſad effects and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents of exporting our Wooll, Fullers earth, &amp;c. as alſo of the idleneſs of our poor people, occaſioned by the loſs of forreign Markets, for our woollen Manufactures; that I think it is high time for all Loyal Subjects, to give their utmoſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance to diſcover all Offenders, and make them manifeſt in their kind, and for all Superiors to give their juſt aſſiſtance that the Lawes may be put into a ſpeedy and ſevere executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt all Delinquents as ſoon as made viſible.</p>
               <p>In the dayes of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third (formerly ſpoken of) and ſince, to the times of our late unhappy confeſions, the Trade of Clothing made the Kingdome flouriſh for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years together, and doubtleſs would do ſo again, if our Lawes were but put into Execution, and every one were obliged to diſcover, and make manifeſt the Tranſgreſſors, for this is not a buſineſs for two or three men to do, let them imploy themſelves with all endeavours imaginable, but the eyes of all men muſt be about this matter, tending to ſuch a Reformation; and the Courts of Judicature muſt be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious and ſevere in the adminiſtration of Juſtice againſt ſuch Offenders, when once convicted, and let not one of them be ſpared, who deſerve to be puniſhed without mercy: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:40315:24"/>
for a little private advantage, they do their utmoſt to bring ruine on the whole kingdome: I could alſo declare o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things that might be very aſſiſtant to the increaſe of Trade, and the proſperity of the Kingdome, which is not ſo convenient to be made publique, before it be debated among the Clothiers and Tradeſmen.</p>
               <p>It hath pleaſed his Majeſty to plant ſuch Commiſſioners now, for the management of his Cuſtomes, that it is hoped they will do much good, eſpecially in the regulation of the Out-Ports, concerning thoſe notorious evil practiſes, which have been continually done among them, and for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging of thoſe Officers that are honeſt and faithful, if they ſhould be troubled at any time, or be any wayes dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified about lawful ſeizures, by reaſon of Actions brought againſt them, that they ſhall be releived by the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and the charges that may ariſe in ſuch caſes at the Law, to be born by the common ſtock.</p>
               <p>I could ſay ſomething for the Staplers, though not much,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Concerning Staplers. Quaere</hi> 1.</note> becauſe I cannot find by our Lawes, that any ſuch people were in thoſe dayes, when the Trade and Manufacture of Wooll was firſt brought into <hi>England;</hi> and yet Wooll was ſent to the Staples, and all the Manufacturers thereof, had thoſe ſorts that ſuited beſt for their trade, and we got and kept the whole trade of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> wooll, and of other Countries to our ſelves, in this Kingdome, and had the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the forreign Markets, which was the occaſion of the firſt ſetling all thoſe Companies, as hath been formerly and briefly ſet forth; and I doubt not, but that thoſe Staplers will ſet a gloſs upon their buſineſs, and without queſtion their money doth ſpeak much for them, lying for the moſt part in and about <hi>London,</hi> ſo near to the Fountain of the Lawes; yet I do verily beleive thoſe people have much to anſwer for, as to the ruine of many poor people, occaſioned by their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation of Wooll beyond Sea, by which evil practice, the Trade of the kingdome is in a great meaſure loſt, as hath been ſet forth already ſomething largely; by reaſon where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:40315:24"/>
many of our poor people in the kingdome are ready to periſh for want of Bread, notwithſtanding the great plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the Land, and this is becauſe they want work.</p>
               <p>I ſhould loſe time further to complain, ſeeing all people are experimentally ſenſible of the loſs and decay of Trade, to the great diſadvantage of the Nobility, and Gentry in the Land, as alſo to the great detriment of the Farmer, and Merchant; although indeed the Poor are moſt pinchingly ſenſible hereof, throughout the King's Dominions, and hence ariſeth the want of Money, (the thing by all men complained of) and the fall of Rents occaſioned thereby.</p>
               <p>I ſhall now proceed by way of <hi>Quaery,</hi> to propound and inſinuate ſomething, that may tend towards a remedy, for theſe Maladies, formerly complain'd of, and to be a reſtora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to our decaying Trade, and to help it to life again; for as Phyſitians having found out the cauſe of the Diſtemper, know the readier how to apply what is ſutable, in order to the Cure. So here I having I hope diſcovered the cauſes, and occaſions of our loſe of Trade, ſhall take the boldneſs to give in tacitly my advice, moſt humbly begging pardon for ſuch a preſumption, and in all ſubmiſſion, preſenting my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions to better judgements.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>VVHether it would not be convenient to have a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Clothiers, ſome of the principal of all Counties, with Merchants of the ſeveral Cities, and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Tradeſmen, and Artificers, to be appointed; whoſe other weighty affairs might not obſtruct this great deſign of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving and advancing our Trade, to its former height, and luſter, and that ſome of thoſe Gentlemen ſit at a certain known place, as their occaſions may permit, ſo that ſome of them may be ready at all times, to receive Petitions, or Projecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from workmen, which may any way tend to the encreaſe and encouragement of Trade; and for ſuch Committees, to prepare and digeſt the ſame, into ſuch a Method and form, as might occaſion the Production of ſuch further Lawes (if
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:40315:25"/>
ſo thought neceſſary) for the future, as might reſtore and advance the Clothing Trade, and the well making of Cloth, and all ſorts of goods, both in the old and new Drapery; and the rectifying ſuch abuſes among all other Tradeſmen, that are any way imployed about the ſaid Draperies.</p>
               <p>Whether all thoſe Laws againſt Exportation, and Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quaere</hi> 2.</note> of Prohibited goods, and for the puniſhment of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithful Officers of the Cuſtomes, and others intruſted that do connive at ſuch abuſes (to the King and Kingdome) and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the faithful performance of their duty, ought not to be put into effectual Execution, and whether all other Lawes, tending to the ſame matter, or have any relation to theſe things, ought not once in a moneth, upon the market day to be publiquely read and declared, eſpecially in the Sea-Port townes, round about the Land, that by this means all the common people, who have the beſt and greateſt opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties for diſcovering Offenders, might know the Law, and ſo conſequently know how, and wherein to do the King and Countrey ſervice, ſuch as might be very acceptable to them, and ſhould not be unprofitable to themſelves, if they would be careful and diligent to watch and look out.</p>
               <p>Whether all people ought not to be encouraged, that ſhall<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quaere</hi> 3.</note> diſcover ſuch as Tranſport Prohibited goods, either into the Kingdome or out of it; and that care ſhould be taken for them in a very ſpecial manner, that they might be protected from vexatious Suits, and Troubles, which are uſually brought upon them that do diſcover ſuch tranſgreſſors, that ſo others may be terrified from ſuch like diſcoveries, all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though therein, by making known ſuch Smugglers, that they may receive the juſtice of the Law, they do the King and Kingdome the higheſt ſervice that may be; and that care may be taken how their Credits, Families and Fortunes may be preſerved againſt the malice of ſuch Miſcreants, whoſe common practice is to multiply troubles on all ſuch as do any way moleſt them in their unjuſt deſignes.</p>
               <p>Whether the evil preſidents, on ſome faithful Officers (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quaere</hi> 4.</note>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:40315:25"/>
vexed and moleſted by theſe Smugglers and their Adhae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents) for doing their duty and being juſt in their places, for the publique good both of King and Kingdome, may not give occaſion to many other Officers, to take Bribes, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with thoſe Smugglers to cheat his Majeſty of his due Cuſtomes, rather than to run the hazard of ſuch moleſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to the utter ruine of themſelves and Families.</p>
               <p>Whether it may not be neceſſary to put thoſe Laws into<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quaere</hi> 5.</note> Execution, that appointed Staples on purpoſe to ſell Wooll at, and that none ſhould be bought, ſold, or bargained for but in the publique Market, by the Clothiers, or the Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facturers therof, or ſhould be carryed too or from, any place or lodged near the water-ſide, under any pretence whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, without the Licences of ſome Officers, appointed on purpoſe, except only in the day-time, by publique and open carriages from the place of its growth, to the publique Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, ſo that all thoſe which ſhall carry Wooll concealed, and others who with force of armed men in the night, tranſport it to the water ſide, in order to their private Shipping it off, with as much obſcurity as they can, might be diſcovered by ſome honeſt Shepherds, Husbandmen, Porters, or Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, whoſe occaſions call them to be abroad both early and late, and ſo they have more convenient opportunities to find out ſuch evil doers, than other people have; and that ſuch as do give in Information of ſuch tranſgreſſors, ſhall be Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected and well rewarded.</p>
               <p>Whether the wilful tranſgreſſion of the Laws of the Land,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quaere</hi> 6.</note> made &amp; ſetled by the King, Lords &amp; Commons in Parliament, &amp; continued in, &amp; obſtinately practiſed; be not the ready if not the only Introduction to Rebellion, when ſuch evil doers, as have been formerly ſpoke of, do make it their utmoſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, to deſtroy the publique for a little private advantage, as hath been already ſo much complained of, having no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the Laws of the Land, that Prohibit ſuch evil pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices as theirs, and whether this be not a high contempt of the Authority aforeſaid, that Enacted thoſe good Lawes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:40315:26"/>Whether it would not forward the great work of revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quaere</hi> 7</note> our Trade, and prevent thoſe abuſes complained of, if an Office was appointed in every County, to be kept by ſome honeſt upright men, who have a clear reſpect to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique good, and advancing the National Trade, that might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive all Informations of ſuch abuſes, and tranſgreſſions of the Laws of the Land, in the caſe before mentioned, from any people that ſhould be the diſcoverers of the ſame, and that ſuch Officers may have power to examine Witneſs up<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on Oath, and if there be found a real guilt, in the Accuſed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons, that ſuch Officer ſhall give to ſuch diſcoverer, of his or their good ſervice, and the matter to be Proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at Law by a publique charge; and the perſons, though never ſo mean, that have given the Informations, ſhould be aſſured to receive his reward, by vertue of his Certificate, without any manner of trouble or charge to himſelf, as ſoon as the Suit ſhall be determined; all which would be carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on with much eaſe, and be accompliſhed in a ſhort time if ſuch an Officer as did Proſecute for the King had the counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Courts of Judicature as they ought to have, and the Cities and Countries made throughly ſenſible, that this matter is of ſo great concernment to the publique good, ſo that all Smugglers might be ſo much diſcountenanced, by all people both high and low, that none ſhould dare to preſume to tranſgreſs the King's Laws, or for the future, endeavour a publique deſtruction to the Kingdome, for their private and perticuler advantage.</p>
               <p>Whether it may not be judged to be more convenient, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quaere</hi> 8.</note> the diſcovery of ſuch Offenders, to Proſecute them in the King's Court of Exchequer, rather than in any Countrey Court adjacent, where ſuch Fact was committed; or where the Offender dwells, leaſt there ſhould be ſome ſpecial cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence held thereabouts, or intereſt more readily made in ſuch Courts.</p>
               <p>In caſe any publique Officer ſhould be ſurprized, by the<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quaere</hi> 9.</note> ſubtil contrivance of ſuch Smugglers, with their Atturnies and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:40315:26"/>
Clerks, (who frequently uſe foul practices alſo,) and that ſuch Officer ſhall be put to great Charges, poſſibly beyond his Ability, before he can obtain releif according to the rules of the Law: whether it would not be convenient that ſuch Rules ſhould be made and practiced in all Courts of Judicature, that ſuch publique Officers for the King, ſhould not be expoſed to ſo great charges, by Actions brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, meerly out of malice, which are done purely out of deſign to terrify ſuch Officers, (and to prevent if poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, for the future, the due and faithful Execution of their ſaid Office in ſuch caſes, wherein the Kingdomes good is ſo much concerned, and that a place was appointed where they might be ſpeedily-heard without tedious attendance.</p>
               <p>Whether any Officer that formerly did, or now doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quaere.</hi> 10.</note> to the Cuſtomes, or was any wayes intruſted in his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Service, who hath proved unjuſt, and unfaithful in his Office, either by conniving at ſuch Smugglers, or complying with them, or negliectng (upon complaint made to him) to bring them to condigne puniſhment, according to the Juſtice of the Law, ought ever to be intruſted in any publique Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment for the future.</p>
               <p>Whether by our Laws, any Under Sheriff ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quaere</hi> 11.</note> in his Office, more than one year, or to act as Under-Sheriff upon any pretence whatſoever; conſidering they have ſuch opportunities, to be prejudicial to any perſon, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their Intereſts, and inclinations; and they may delay and vex one party, and in the mean time unjuſtly incourage, and heighten the other; and this is ſuch a thing as often proves very prejudicial to His Majeſties Affairs in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of ſuch Informations, as may be brought, touching the abuſes here mentioned.</p>
               <p>Whether theſe Officers, that are in Commiſſion or Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quaere</hi> 12.</note> that do joyn with, or countenance ſuch as do tranſgreſs the King's Laws, and make it their buſineſs to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud the King of his Dues, or are not ready and forward to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:40315:27"/>
do that iuſtice againſt the Delinquents that ſo do, ought not to be Diſplaced, and ſome way ſeverely Puniſhed?</p>
               <p>Whether thoſe Jurors that will give up their Verdict con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quaere</hi> 13.</note> to Law, and Evidence, ought not to be forced to give ſatisfaction to the party ſo greived, and injured; or to be made to ſuffer one way or another, as examples in ſuch caſes; without any tedious trouble to the party greived, as may be judged requiſite, and reaſonable; for as our Laws ſtand in that caſe, it is almoſt impoſſible to puniſh a Jury that doth offend, and act contrary to Law; for it is too much become the cuſtome of many Juries, to act to the dammage of one perſon, out of favour and reſpect to the other, ſo that all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are ſenſible of the great abuſes that are put upon one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, where the Adverſary can carry a great intereſt, either in Cities or Countrey.</p>
               <p>Whether it would not be as great a renown to His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quaere</hi> 14.</note> if the Trade of Clothing was recovered to its height, as it was to King <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, of Famous Memory, by whoſe Providence, and Induſtry it was firſt brought into <hi>England,</hi> which hath been ſo exceedingly advantagious to this Kingdome, for many years, and doubtleſs might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived, to as great a ſtrength as ever; if ſuch things were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted and practiced, which might be the proper and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual means, conducible thereunto; and the people of the Kingdome brought to a ready obſervation, of the Lawes of the Land, which would turn to his Majeſties great advantage in his Cuſtomes, &amp;c. and put all his Subjects in general into a capacity of paying their Taxes willingly, according as his Majeſty ſhould have occaſion, the Springs of Trade then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing open and running, would bring in ſupplies to all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quaere</hi> 15.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Whether it would not be neceſſary that all theſe Laws not yet Repealed, relating to the furtherance of Trade and promiſcuouſly ſcattered in the Law Books, ought not to be revived, and re-Printed in one Volume, that ſo all people might readily know thoſe Laws, and be by Authority ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:40315:27"/>
commanded the obſervance of the ſame, with incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quaere</hi> 17.</note> to the obedient, and puniſhments to the diſobedient.</p>
               <p>In caſe any Laws be wanting, or are not full enough, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Tranſportation of our Prohibited goods, or the Importation of Forreign Prohibited goods, as new ſorts of Stuffs, that may be made beyond Sea, or any thing elce, that is not perticularly provided againſt, whether it may not be very neceſſary to have ſuch a defect ſupplyed.</p>
               <p>Whether there ought not to be a Statute for the regulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quaere</hi> 16.</note> or well making of ſuch Stuffs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which were not uſed in former times, that ſo all deceits in work may be avoided, which if done, would doubtleſs very much advance the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> goods, and greatly further the ſale of them at a Forreign Market.</p>
               <p>Whether it is convenient that our Manufactures of Cloth<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quaere</hi> 18.</note> and Stuffs, ſhould be allowed to be tranſported out of the Land white (or undied) becauſe it is a very common pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> too, ſo to do, and then they Dye them and Dreſs them in <hi>Holland,</hi> by the which they ſet many people on work, and all that imployment is loſt to <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland:</hi> but this is not all, for the Dutch do ſo handle the matter, as that they mak our own goods more acceptable and ſaleable in Forreign Countries, than we uſually do, with the ſame ſort of goods which we Dy in <hi>England,</hi> to the great profi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and credit of the <hi>Dutch</hi> abroad among ſtrangers, and to the great loſs and dammage of <hi>England,</hi> beſides the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reputation by that means to <hi>England,</hi> yea many times the ſame goods that were carryed over to <hi>Holland</hi> white, are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to us again, when the <hi>Dutch</hi> have Dyed them and dreſſed them, and then they are eſteemed the beſt Colours, and therefore moſt vendible among us.</p>
               <p>Whether it would not be very conducible to the publique<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quaere</hi> 19.</note> good, that thoſe perticuler Statutes ſhould be put into effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Execution, which do poſitively appoint, that all Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants Forreigners, Tradeing into <hi>England</hi> with Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities of their own Countrey growth, and vending them
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:40315:28"/>
here, ſhould lay out their money again in our Engliſh Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactures, and not be permitted to carry money out of the Land, directly nor indirectly; but lay it out in the goods, and wares of <hi>England</hi> (their neceſſary expences excepted) according to the true intent and meaning of the ſaid Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute.</p>
               <p>Whether it be not worthy to be taken into conſideration, concerning the fineneſs and weight of our Engliſh Coin; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quere</hi> 20.</note> and beyond the Coin of our neighbouring Nations, and whether that be not the cauſe of its Exportation out of the Land; a broad twenty ſhillings peice of Gold, being worth in <hi>France, Flanders,</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> twenty ſeven ſhillings, and a Crown piece of ſilver worth ſix ſhillings; ſo that I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe we may ceaſe wondring, what is become of the money of the Kingdome, conſidering it is ſuch profit to the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant to tranſport it beyond Sea.</p>
               <p>Whether it would not very much increaſe Trading, and be highly advantageous to the King's Majeſty, to have mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quaere</hi> 21.</note> plentiful in the Land, and greatly benefit the Common-Weale, if money in <hi>England</hi> was in ſome meaſure made ſutable or equal, to the weight and fineneſs of money in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Lands, and whether this would not be a great means of bringing in money from other Lands, and then keep it in the Kingdome being brought in; by ſuch means the King would be ſure to have a ſpeedy ſupply on all demands, for his occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and it is granted on all hands, that good Treaſures of Money are the principal Sinews of War.</p>
               <p>Whether we in <hi>England,</hi> ought not in reaſon, to take the<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quere</hi> 22.</note> ſame care, for the preſervation and advancement of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Commodities, as every other Kingdome and Countrey doth for theirs, as in <hi>Spain,</hi> the labour of the people is in their Vineyards, for the Production of Wine and Fruit, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which they take great care, that they make the ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, and ſpend little of theſe things themſelves, that they may make money of them to furniſh their needs, with what is ſutable, and many times they will not part with theſe their
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:40315:28"/>
goods, for Barter, or Exchange for other goods, but will have ready money, and at dear rates too, as I have heard by thoſe that have traded into thoſe parts; ſome have given to the Spaniards, at the <hi>Canaries</hi> 100 peices of Eight, for an ordinary Pipe of Wine, in ready money; which 100 Peices of Eight are well worth twenty two pounds Sterling, with us, and likewiſe in <hi>France</hi> concerning their Wines, Salt, Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> what care is by them taken to make the beſt of them, that may be, and what vaſt quantities of French-Wines, Brandy, Vinegar, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> do come over into <hi>England</hi> in a year; to pay for which I doubt, there goes a great deal of ready money: and if ſo in other Countries, why ſhould not the ſame care be taken in <hi>England,</hi> for the advancement of our Manufactures, endeavouring thereby to imploy our Poor, and ſo to inrich the Kingdome, eſpecially conſidering the far greater advantages of ſo doing, that we have in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> than any other Nation hath, as hath been already at large ſet forth.</p>
               <p>Why ſhould the humour of our people in <hi>England</hi> ſo far<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quere</hi> 23.</note> engage them to an old cuſtome of burying the dead in Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen, as to contradict and diſobey ſo good a Law as was lately made by Act of Parliament, for the burial of our dead in Woollen, doubtleſs there was reaſon enoug then produced in Parliament, to ſway with the King and thoſe two Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Houſes for the Enacting the ſame, and whether it be not as decent to cover the dead Corps in Flannel, as it is with Linnen; beſide the burial of the dead in Flannel will great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly advance the Manufacture of the Nation, and in reaſon ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the prizes of all other Woollen wares, and this Wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len Cloth is of our own production, and when we bury our people in Linne, that cauſeth ſo much expence (for the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality) of the goods of other Countries; and whether it ought not to be conſidered, that the Law provided in this caſe, ought to be re-inforced.</p>
               <p>Now to draw towards an end, I have met with an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to this Treatiſe, that it may be judged Superflous,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:40315:29"/>
becauſe ſeveral Books are errant concerning this Subject; to which I Anſwer.</p>
               <p>Though I have reaſon to beleive them that told me ſo, yet I do beleive that the Reader will find a great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween this and any other, if they be compared together, and that in many reſpects.</p>
               <p>And again I Anſwer, that the more Complaints are made, of the Abuſes and great Loſſes to the Kingdome, ſo much the more ought all good men to enquire into the truth of thoſe Complaints, and endeavour for ſutable Remedies; in Tendency whereto, I have preſented ſomething here by way of Quaere, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now methinks I hear ſome wiſe men ſay, that it is Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that ſuch abuſes ſhould be puniſhed, and that ſeverely, if any ſhould preſume to act ſuch things, as are here com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of, or any waies vindicate thoſe that do them; to the which I anſwer, that I wiſh that I were called to prove my knowledge of thoſe things, without too much charge or At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance, before any that ſhould be appointed, to enquire into and to regulate the ſame, for I do not make it my buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to ſet forth in this diſcourſe the perticuler abuſes of thoſe Countrey Atturneys, Under-Clerks, Under-Sheriffs in their returns, and the abuſes of their Officers, and the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance that ſome great Smugglers have, from ſome Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates and Juſtices of the Peace in the Countrey, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the affronts that have been offered to our good Lawes, of which I have had a large and ſad experience: And although our Lawes are good, and our Judges are juſt, yet the corruption in the practice of the Law, by under-Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, is ſo exceeding bad and deſtructive to the Trade and publique good of the Kingdome, that in caſe I ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly recite thoſe abuſes that I my ſelf have met with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Practicers of the Law, I ſhould fill a Book many times bigger than this.</p>
               <p>And now I ſhall conclude, with the true and hearty wiſhes of an <hi>Engliſhman,</hi> that all our Miniſters of State may ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:40315:29"/>
eſpecially in this juncture of time, that they may una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly joyn together, as one intire body, againſt all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truders upon our Trade and Priveledges both at Sea and Land; that the Walls of this Kingdome may be built up and preſerved, and our Tradeing may encreaſe and flouriſh, ſo that no cunning Uſurpers may rob us of our old Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of the Seas, or the Manufacture of our native Trade up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Land.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:40315:30"/>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:40315:30"/>
            <head>In Laudem Authoris &amp; Subjecti.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>HAd I but lived in <hi>Ben. Johnſons</hi> dayes</l>
               <l>I would have learn't of him, to ſpeak the Praiſe</l>
               <l>Of Native <hi>Engliſh Wooll,</hi> and to ſet forth</l>
               <l>It's real Excellency and it's worth</l>
               <l>The Poets tell us of the <hi>Golden Fleece</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That <hi>Jaſon</hi> undertook to fetch to <hi>Greece.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But that's a Fiction, ours a real thing</l>
               <l>Which to the Kingdome doth great Riches bring</l>
               <l>So that no Nation to us might compare</l>
               <l>If diligent in working it, we were,</l>
               <l>The <hi>French</hi> with all their Salt, Brandy and Wine,</l>
               <l>Could not afford to Cloath themſelves ſo fine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The <hi>Spaniſh-India</hi> Mines do not yield forth</l>
               <l>Such Riches as our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Cloth is worth,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſcanty Cloaks and Bagpipe Hoſe</l>
               <l>Do go from <hi>England,</hi> as each Trav'ler knows.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Dutch mens</hi> Suits of Clothes and Buſhel knees</l>
               <l>From <hi>England</hi> are Tranſported ore the Seas.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The <hi>Portugal</hi> delights to wear our Bayes</l>
               <l>The <hi>Negro</hi> doth as much affect our <hi>Sayes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Turk</hi> doth highly prize our broader Wear</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:40315:31"/>The <hi>Grecian</hi> herein with him do compare,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Hamborough</hi> our Broad Clothes go a main</l>
               <l>By which thoſe Merchants do receive their gain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To <hi>Ruſhia</hi> and <hi>Muſcovy</hi> likewiſe goes</l>
               <l>Good ſtore of broad, and narrow Woollen Clothes.</l>
               <l>And all the Eaſt Lands ore ſuch is the Trade</l>
               <l>For Woollen Clothes, in <hi>England</hi> which are made.</l>
               <l>Into <hi>Eaſt India</hi> ſtore of Cloth we ſend</l>
               <l>As faſt as the <hi>Eaſt India</hi> Company can vend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Who find great profit to accrue thereby</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto that Honourable Company;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Indians</hi> in <hi>America</hi> do wear</l>
               <l>The <hi>Duffels</hi> which with us prepared are,</l>
               <l>And in Exchange do give us <hi>Bever</hi> Skins</l>
               <l>Which to the Nation good Riches brings.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto <hi>Peru</hi> and unto <hi>Mexico</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Much of our Woollen Manufactures go,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Portugal (Brazeel</hi> inhabiting)</l>
               <l>For Clothing doth delight in no ſuch thing</l>
               <l>As <hi>Engliſh</hi> Bayes and Stuffes which they do wear</l>
               <l>Which unto them by Sea Tranſported are.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The <hi>Perſian</hi> Silks, and from th' <hi>Armenians</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So highly prized by th' <hi>Italians,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Are but for Summer wear, for there is not</l>
               <l>Such thickneſs in that dreſs to keep them hot</l>
               <l>In Winter, as there is in <hi>Engliſh</hi> Clothes</l>
               <l>When as the bluſtring <hi>Boreas</hi> ſtif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y blowes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And of ſuch goods in <hi>England</hi> we don't lack</l>
               <l>To Cloath and to adorn our Gentries back,</l>
               <l>Which for Exchange of Cloth our Merchants bring</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:40315:31"/>(Together alſo with each pleaſant thing.</l>
               <l>Which is Imported to us by the Seas</l>
               <l>While we it'h houſe can make our Cloth with eaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus now you ſee the World was furniſh't well</l>
               <l>With Cloth and Stuff which <hi>Engliſh men</hi> did ſell,</l>
               <l>But <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> intruded have of late</l>
               <l>And with us in the Trade participate.</l>
               <l>The fault's our own, becauſe they get our Wooll,</l>
               <l>And then they do improve it to the full.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This makes me that I am exceeding loath</l>
               <l>To loſe the work, and profit of our Cloth,</l>
               <l>Which comes unto the Poor as well as Rich</l>
               <l>And therefore now I humbly do beſeech<note place="margin">Houſe of Lords.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Thoſe that on Wooll-Packs ſit, to puniſh thoſe</l>
               <l>That Ship away our Wooll, not made in Clothes.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. S<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:40315:32"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40315:32"/>
            <head>Poſcript.</head>
            <p>THat theſe things are conſiderable to be looked into, and that a ſtock may be raiſed to employ the poor out of miſimployed Charity, I have given a breif account of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes of Charity, in the place where I now inhabit, with a ſhort Deſcription of the River of <hi>Medway,</hi> alias <hi>Chatham,</hi> and the fraudes practiſed there and of ſome notorious abuſes put upon me for doing my duty, and endeavouring to prevent thoſe fraudes complained of in this Book, with the foul Practiſe of ſome under-Clerks, and cunning devices of ſome other Lawyers, which I ſhall Preſent to his moſt Sacred Majeſty, and to the great Councils of the Kingdome; to the end it may be known what need there is of better encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to honeſt Officers, and thoſe who put the Laws in Execution againſt ſuch Offenders, being alſo ready to prove what is alledged in every particular clauſe before his Majeſty in Councel.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:40315:33"/>
               <hi>England</hi> is exceeding happy in a good and gracious King, but extreamly unhappy in ſome unfaithful Officers, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided people, we are alſo happy in good Lawes, but unhappy in that they are ſo much corrupted, it is nothing with ſome Councel to make good, bad, and bad, good; and in caſe they abuſe a man never ſo much, this is ſufficient, <hi>They ought to do what they can for their Client:</hi> by this courſe, our moſt gracious King, and the Honourable Courts are often miſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, honeſt men diſcouraged, and unjuſt Stewards pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, let Attorneys and Clerks uſe never ſo unjuſt practice, honeſt and juſt Lawyers will ſeldome complain, or move a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe of the ſame profeſſion. This Nation is puffed up with Pride, and grown idle with plenty, the meaneſt vie with the greateſt, and will do any unjuſt thing to maintain it, Playes are more regarded then Prayers, Drunkenneſs than Study, the Clerks pens, than Trades-mens hands, ſo that our Trade is loſt, our people live idle, Charity Robbed, our Poor ſtarved, our Lawes not regarded, our Conſciences faſt a ſleep.</p>
            <p>The Scene is ſo much altered in 25. or 30 years, that then a man thought his Son well provided for, if placed with a Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier, and now nothing will do but Law, ſo that they multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply like Catterpillers in a dry Summer, inſomuch that the increaſe of the Land cannot feed them, but they ſwallow up the earth alſo, what I write is no Romance, I have had ſad experience of the truth of it, and according to the good old Proverbs, <hi>The Loſer may have leave to ſpeak, And truth may be blamed, though not ſhamed,</hi> that doth make a man as bold as a Lion, and I bleſs God in all my ſad Afflictions, that very thing, and God's promiſes hath kept up my ſpirits, and without reaſon I ſtill hoped to be delivered from thoſe wolves, as <hi>Daniel</hi> was delivered out of the Lyons Den, which hath been done, ſome of my Enemies falling before me, and others have confeſſed their faults, and I have as freely forgiven them, as I hope God will forgive me, others whoſe actions are ſo foul, they bluſh and hang down their heads when
<pb facs="tcp:40315:33"/>
they ſee me, though they will endeavour behind my back, &amp; where it's not known, to excuſe themſelves, I declare I deſire to be in peace with all men, though I do endeavour to get my right, vindicate my ſelf, and for publique good puniſh Offenders.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Vale.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
